<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The remonstrance from the Reverend Father in God, Francis Lord Bishop of Ely, and several others, the most eminent divines of the Church of England, against the proceedings of the P: O. and the lords spiritual and temporal, that invited him. Being an adress [sic], from the pulpit to the King, in fifteen sermons; denouncing damnation, &amp;c. to the abdicators of God's annoynted, and abettors of this rebellion.</title>
            <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 197 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B10212</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80924892</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R185788</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80924892</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80924892</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192125</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B10212)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192125)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2900:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The remonstrance from the Reverend Father in God, Francis Lord Bishop of Ely, and several others, the most eminent divines of the Church of England, against the proceedings of the P: O. and the lords spiritual and temporal, that invited him. Being an adress [sic], from the pulpit to the King, in fifteen sermons; denouncing damnation, &amp;c. to the abdicators of God's annoynted, and abettors of this rebellion.</title>
                  <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 72, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Alderman James Malone ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"These sermons may be printed, Dublin Castle the 28th of July 1689. Patrick Clogher"--P. [2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland) Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:192125:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE REMONSTRANCE From the Reverend Father in God, FRANCIS LORD BISHOP Of ELY, And ſeveral others, The moſt Eminent DIVINES Of the CHURCH Of ENGLAND, Againſt The Proceedings of the P: O. And The Lords Spiritual and Temporal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That Invited Him. Being an <hi>ADRESS,</hi> from the <hi>P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPIT</hi> to the <hi>KING,</hi> in fifteen <hi>Sermons;</hi> Denouncing <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> &amp;c. To the <hi>Abdicators</hi> of God's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted, and the <hi>Abettors</hi> of this Rebellion.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Concilia callida et Inhoneſta, pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Fronte loeta, Tractatudura, Eventu triſtia, <bibl>Tacitus.</bibl>
               </hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Dublin,</hi> Printed for Alderman <hi>James Malone</hi> Book-ſeller in <hi>Skinner-Row.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:192125:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192125:2"/>
            <head>TO THE SACRED MAJESTY OF God's Annointed AND Vice-Gerent to the Almighty;</head>
            <p>IAMES The Second by the Grace of God of England, Scotland, France, and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, KING.</p>
            <p>In Vindication of the Principles of Obedience and Loyalty, always Taught by the Church of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Remonſtrance is moſt humbly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By your Majeſties ever Loyal and Dutiful Subject. JOHN YALDEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:192125:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>PArdon me, if I preſume to uſe the King words, at his Majeſties firſt Acceſſion to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Crown <hi>(viz.) I know the Principles of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Church of England, are for Loyalty;</hi> And <hi>I</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> tell I hee too, that Loyalty will be always co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, where it is accompanied with True Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. If thou doeſt enquire of me, whether the Preachers of the Goſpel, have fully practice thoſe indiſpenſible principles, of primitive a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> pure Chriſtianity, herein taught and avowed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them, to the whole world? <hi>I</hi> can only tell Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> (with the Heathen Orator) <hi>Omnis laus virtut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, actione conſiſtit;</hi> If any of them have acted contra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to what they delivered to the People from t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Pulpit</hi> (where none but Sacred <hi>Oracles</hi> ſhould diſpenced) it is they only are too blame, And t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>I</hi> am affraid, Even my <hi>Biſhop</hi> here cannot through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excuſe himſelf, yet ſuch as are innocent ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, ought not, in Juſtice to ſhare in thoſe Bit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Reproaches, which are moſt juſtly due to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Guilty.</hi> Tho the late Defection in <hi>England,</hi> was ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> general, and ſpread it ſelf over his Majeſties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions like the poiſonous infection of an Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical <hi>Contagion,</hi> yet <hi>I</hi> know there are many l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and thoſe <hi>Proteſtants</hi> too, that have not bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> their knees to <hi>Baal,</hi> nor worſhiped the <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:192125:3"/> Calf,</hi> that others have ſett up, ſuch as will moſt aſſuredly, joyn with the King, upon afair oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, and do now really believe it to be a kind of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> to obey the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> hath followed his Majeſtie, through all the <hi>Meanders,</hi> of his moſt Barbarous <hi>Exile,</hi> and is deſign'd chiefly to reclaim ſuch of his Subjects, to their duty as have been miſlead; &amp; bring them to a due conſideration of that natural and ſworn <hi>Allegiance!</hi> which for the moſt part, both ways, They owe the King: And to aſſure the Obſtinat perſiſting Rebell, that his Portion ſhall be, amidſt all the dire effects of Eternal venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, accompanied with the Curſed Crew of <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtat</hi> Angels, ſtill Curſing <hi>God,</hi> as they Curſe the <hi>King,</hi> becauſe <hi>They</hi> can expect no <hi>Mercy, by</hi> being Sunk below the Depth of all Repentance.</p>
            <p>The firſt 14 of theſe <hi>Sermons</hi> were preach'd on the <hi>9th</hi> of <hi>September</hi> 1683, being a <hi>day</hi> ſet apart for the moſt Solemn <hi>worſhip</hi> of <hi>God</hi> Almighty, a <hi>day</hi> of <hi>Thanksgiving,</hi> for the great deliverance of his Majeſtie and his <hi>Royal</hi> Brother, from the <hi>Rye</hi> houſe Regicides, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the laſt for the Defeat of <hi>Monmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th's Rebellion.</hi> So that <hi>Sermons</hi> Preached up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch <hi>Occaſions, may</hi> be <hi>truly</hi> taken, as from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons filled with <hi>Extraordinary</hi> Devotion, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired with a true zeal for the Honour of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:192125:4"/>
            <p>To have printed the whole of each <hi>Sermon,</hi> would have been <hi>too</hi> voluminous aſ-well <hi>too</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable to thee. But in this Abſtact, is contain'd the matter, and deſigne of the ſeveral Diſcourſes the Force and Strength of all their <hi>Arguments</hi> where any thing is added, it is only to make a Connection, and comes generally betwixt theſe two marks [ ] And as the <hi>Divinity</hi> of theſe <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi> doth extend itſelf to an univerſal <hi>Obedience</hi> So I hope the Reader will pardon me, where I apply ſuch Doctrines, to the caſe of this <hi>Rebellion;</hi> In fine, <hi>I</hi> challenge any man to ſhew me, that <hi>I</hi> have wreſted any thing contrary to the true ſence of my <hi>Authors</hi> (Tho' perhaps Some Mens own words, at this time a <hi>day,</hi> will be unſavory even to themſelves, but ſuch deſerve the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of <hi>Atheiſts</hi> much better than that of <hi>Honeſt</hi> Chriſtians) And to that purpoſe <hi>I</hi> have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the moſt Malicious <hi>Critick</hi> where to find the <hi>Sermons,</hi> by telling him for whom they were Printed.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:192125:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON ENTITULED The Duties of Fearing God and The King, Preach'd on the <hi>9th</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> 1683. by <hi>John Fitz William D. D.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Prov. 24. verſ. 21, 22.</bibl>
               <q>My Son, Fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change. For their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the ruine of them both?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>FEaring God and the King are Duties inſeparable. Indeed all the Commands are ſo chain'd together, that he who looſens but a ſingle link, diſſolves the whole chain; who tranſgreſſeth one, is guilty of all. For tho they were wrote in two diſtinct Tables, and diſtributed under ten heads, or words, (as the Jewiſh Docters ſpeak) by God himſelf; yet his Authority, being the ſoul which quickned them, (like the ſoul anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſeveral members of the body; gave them all but one common life and being: So that a particular violation of one, becomes of acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity an univerſal deſtruction to all. And as the Commands, ſo our obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations to obſerve them are connext; if not after that manner as <hi>Zeno</hi> affirm'd all virtues were, (who promiſcuouſly confounded them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:) yet ſo, as <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yſippus</hi> hath explain'd that Stoical Doctrine, That a man could not be truly Brave without the conduct of Prudence; nor
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:192125:5"/> Prudent, without attending to Juſtice; nor Juſt, without the regulation of Temperance: So in like manner, a man cannot be piouſly affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, without being honeſtly affected towards Men; cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs his Love towards the one (in the inſtances belonging to him,) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhewing it towards the other, in all points which concern them; and he who pretends to the former: And neglects the latter, proclaims himſelf a liar.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of this is plain and obvious, becauſe if I perform the firſt from a right principle, out of conſcience of my duty towards God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it; the ſame principle will engage me to do the ſecond, becauſe he demands that likewiſe. And on the other ſide, if the motive of my love to my fellow Creature man, be his bearing the image of God, I cannot but love and reverence that God, who faſhion'd him after his own like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>And as there is no dividing, ſo there is no commuting of duties; our zeal in one kind, will not make attonement for our remiſneſs in another; our Piety for Injuſtice.</p>
            <p>But tho'all the commands are inſeparably conjoyn'd, yet there is a clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer and more <hi>indiſſoluble union</hi> between theſe two particular ones of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earing God and the King,</hi> by how much Kings are more lively expreſſions of God's Majeſty and Power, than ordinary images (other men) are. The wiſe Man hath here mention'd them as one command; and St. <hi>Peter</hi> too, even while he uſeth two words for them, <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Honour, Fear God, Honour the King,</hi> for this honouring the King <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 2. 17.</note> is the ſame act, as fearing of him, or expreſſive of it. And Kings for their nearer and exacter reſemblance of him, are adorn'd with his title, wear his name, and have <note place="margin">Pſal. 82. 6. Joh. 10. 34. Exod. 22. 28.</note> his ſtile given them by Himſelf; <hi>I have ſaid Ye are Gods:</hi> and again, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ourſe the Gods..</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this ſtrict alliance and union of theſe two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, ariſing out of the near reſemblance between the perſons, God and the King, and the Majeſty of the one, and Soveraignty of the other; it is made as impoſſible to adore God, and not revere the King, who repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents him; as it is to honour the King, and caſt all the contumely we can upon his Lieutenants, or Vice-Roys, commiſſion'd by him.</p>
            <p>And of neceſſity it follows, that <hi>Subjects withdrawing their Obedience</hi> from their <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Such was and is</hi> James <hi>the Second.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lawful Prince,</hi> is a <hi>deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Authority of God,</hi> a ſhaking off His Government from his Shoulders, a laying Him aſide, that he ſhould
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192125:5"/> not reign over <note n="t" place="margin">The people of England.</note> 
               <hi>Them. They have not rejected Thee, but Me, that I ſhould not reign over them,</hi> 1 Sam. 9. 7.</p>
            <p>Treaſon againſt the King, is a kind of Sacriledge; a Revolt from Him, an Apoſtacy from God; a Reſiſting Him, an Oppoſing God; Rebelling againſt Him, Fighting with God; the <note n="*" place="margin">Is not this the caſe in England.</note> 
               <hi>Setting up a counterfeit Prince</hi> againſt the <hi>True One,</hi> an intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing a plurality of Godheads; the <hi>Obeying of an Uſurper,</hi> Idolatry; the ſlandering His Annointed and his Footſteps, a Blaſpheming God; the blaming His Conduct, a Quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with Providence.</p>
            <p>And as we cannot Fear God, the Supreme Potentate, without Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Subordinate, who bears His Image and Superſcription; ſo we cannot Honour this laſt as we ſhould, without Fearing the former as we ought: We cannot revere the Copy of Divinity tranſcrib'd in the King, without revering the Original, the Deity, front whom His power came, any more than we can have a veneration for the picture of a man, and none for his perſon. We cannot be for maintaining the Prerogative, while we are clipping the wings of his Power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no bearing true Faith and Allegiance to our King, when we do it not to our God; no being loyal Subjects to the One, while we are downright Traytors to the Other. The reaſon of this is clear, becauſe the honouring and obeying our Prince ſhould proceed from a Religion towards God; a conſcientious regard to his Authority, exacting the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of both theſe; which if they do not, they are falſe and ſpurious, wanting the true and genuine Parent (a right principle I mean) for their production, and muſt needs be <note n="*" place="margin">Engliſh Loyalty.</note> 
               <hi>ſickle and inconſtant,</hi> for not being grounded upon a ſure and ſtanding bottom: So that when an <hi>Inviting Occaſion</hi> offers, of promoting our intereſt to greater advantage, of ſerving our ambition with better ſucceſs, than by Honouring or Obeying our King; or of <hi>Gratifying</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Malecontents or diſguſted Lords?</note> 
               <hi>our Revenge,</hi> of <hi>Wreaking our Malice,</hi> then theſe are forgot and withdrawn. Or laſt of all, when by a declination in the ſtate of affairs He is grown too weak, to compel Us to render theſe, <note place="margin">Baxter's Holy Common Wealth, Theſ. 137.</note> then we not only deny the payment of them, but ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify it too. Then maxims of humane Wiſdom, the moſt contrary to theſe precepts of the Divine, are broach'd by Us. That the King is not God's Miniſter, but the Peoples
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:192125:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:192125:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:192125:7"/> Servant; and as theirs, ſtands accountable to them for his miſdemeanors; That his Power being a Truſt only from, and for them, is revokable at their pleaſure and diſcretion, and they may juſtly reſeize it into their own hands, and for their own behoof, when they ſee it is not adminiſtred for their good; That wicked, and irreligious Princes (and all are ſuch whom They pleaſe to brand with thoſe marks) have actually for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited their Crown and Dignity to them: And then <note n="*" place="margin">Too lately in England.</note> 
               <hi>Practices</hi> ſquar'd, or rather deform'd by theſe enormous rules, are ſet on foot too; ſeditious Clubs and Cabals are erected; <hi>Illegal Aſſociations</hi> form'd, and entred into; <hi>Secret Conſpiracies</hi> hatch'd; next <hi>Open Inſurrections</hi> raiſed againſt them; and laſt of all, <hi>Uillanous Aſſaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinations,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A diſdainfull pride ſwell'd Dathan, Abiram and On, Sons of Reuben (and ſo of the eldeſt Houſe) to ſee that power <note place="margin">Numb. 16, 8, 13, 14.</note> lodg'd in <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi>'s hands, which by right of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogeniture, they imagin'd belong'd to them; Ambition ſeduc'd <hi>Abſolom,</hi> the Peoples <hi>Guil.</hi> And Revenge for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.</note> removed from his great Charge, and drove into Exile by <hi>Solomon,</hi> inflam'd <hi>Jereboam</hi> into Rebellion under the <note place="margin">1 Kings 11. 28. 40.</note> Reign of his <hi>Son.</hi> And every one of theſe either forſook God afore they did <note n="*" place="margin">ſuch is the King.</note> 
               <hi>Their Lawfull G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vernours,</hi> or Elſe Renounc'd them and diſclaim'd him together: The Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <hi>Reubenites</hi> were engag'd in a Schiſm againſt God, at the ſame time as they were up in Mutiny againſt their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers; joyn'd themſelves to <hi>Corah,</hi> a Levite, who had Uſurp'd the <hi>Prieſt</hi>'s Office, in Burning Incenſe before the Lord, which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd not to him. <hi>Abſolom</hi> had his hands imbrewed in <note place="margin">2 Sam. 13. 28.</note> his Brother <hi>Amon</hi>'s blood before he lifted them up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Prince and <hi>Father,</hi> and <hi>Jereb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am,</hi> to <note place="margin">1 Kings 12. 27. 28.</note> ſtrengthen himſelf in his unjuſt acquiſitions, made a Change in the Worſhip; to continue the rend in State, by winding it; He made a Rupture in Religion. To defend his Rebellion, he ſet up <hi>Idolatry,</hi> two <hi>Calves</hi> at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to manifeſt that we fear God and honour the <hi>King,</hi> We ought not to meddle with thoſe that are given to Change: And this <note n="*" place="margin">The Biſhops.</note> We may do, either by approving the Projects of <note n="t" place="margin">Lords Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Men Deſigning a Change,</hi> or by actually endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring One our ſelves; and the concerning our ſelves ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:192125:7"/> way is unlawfull: And firſt, the approving a Change Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Us as equally Guilty, as if we had brought it about; for it is conſenting to a Crime, which derives all the malignity of it upon <note n="*" place="margin">who has been to blame.</note> Us; the External Commiſſion of it being only the owning of that to the World, which we had before per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrated within our ſelves: <hi>Cataline</hi> was not leſs a Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, and an Enemy to <hi>Rome,</hi> when he ſat in Conſultation within its Walls, by what methods and parties its frame and conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were to be ſubverted, than when he took the Feild, and Uſurping the Enſigns and Badges of Conſulſhip he joyn'd with C. <hi>Mallius:</hi> And a man may be as compleat a Rebell as he was, without taking up Arms againſt the Government, meerly by juſtifying the Lawfullneſs of ſo doing, a Traytor <note n="†" place="margin">Why did not the Lords Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual abhor, or diſown the <hi>P.</hi> of <hi>O.</hi> Declaration as the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired them.</note> 
               <hi>by Giving a Favourable Ear to Dvertures</hi> tending that way; deep dy'd in the Blood of his Prince, by being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to a deſign of Sheding it; or all over Coal-black with foul Poyſon, which he hath neither prepared nor mingled, by being Privy only to an intention of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring it.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>we</hi> are Guilty in the Courts of Heaven, and our own Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of a Treaſon or Conſpiracy, which hath once <hi>gain'd out likeing,</hi> tho We proceed not to Execution; <note place="margin">Let every Xian Man in England conſider this.</note> ſo we may by the Law of State be juſtly Puniſh'd for the ſame, if that could be prov'd: For although it might be hard, it was not unjuſt, when a Noble-man of <hi>Normandi</hi> was Arreſted and Condemned of Treaſon by the Judges of the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> For an Intention to kill <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt, which he himſelf diſcloſed as a Crime he repented of, and for which he craved the Comfort of Abſolution.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly the endeavouring a <hi>Change</hi> plungeth the perſon (tho he be drawn in by the Artifice of others) over head and ears in guilt, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſeth him as deep in it as the firſt Contriv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and hotteſt promoters of it: For it matters not to the aba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ement of that, what time he engag'd in it, or whether after engagement he was active or ſupine in proſecuting it; nor is it any what meanes he chooſeth to effect it, whether fair or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (as we uſually diſtinguiſh) whether he be for Picking his way, or Reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v'd to venture through Thick and Thin: And in a Crime of this Nature, there are no acceſſaries, but all are Principals</p>
            <p>And further, to endeavour a Change, is contrary to the Duties, ſo oft
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:192125:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:192125:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:192125:9"/> and ſo earneſtly preſſed upon Us in Scripture, of not Touching God's Annointed; of being Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. 15. <hi>Rom. 13. à 1 ad 6. 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 13. 14.</note> to the Higher Powers; of Submitting to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ordinance (of every one Conſtituted in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority) whether to the King as Supreme, or unto Governours, as thoſe that are ſent <hi>[i. e.]</hi> Commiſſioned by him, For is not the Aſſaſſination of God's Annointed, contrary to the Command of not Touching him? <hi>Is</hi> not the <hi>Plucking down Kings</hi> or Rulers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Precept of our Subjection and Submiſſion to Them? Is not the endeavouring to Embroyl the Affairs of his or their Government op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Doctrine of living Peaceably under it? And are not theſe the Methods <hi>We</hi> purſue in Order to bring about a Change? And if they are, they cannot (with all the Allowance of Favour) be ſo Conſtrued, as they may be reconcil'd with our Honouring Him or Them; for it may be as eaſily made out, that you may Smite Them with the Fiſt of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and not Touch them; Raiſe Combuſtions, and not meddle in their Affaires; as Salve the doing theſe with Honouring Them.</p>
            <p>And if there have been Men <hi>among us;</hi> who have taken theſe Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and yet have confidently, or rather Impudently ſtil'd themſelves <hi>his Majeſties moſt Loyal Subjects,</hi> They ought to prove the before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Texts are to be expounded backward, and ſhew us they have found out the Miſterious Art of Salving Contradictions; of making Light and Darkneſs, Order and Confuſion dwell together; Peace and War ſalute and kiſs each other, or Elſe leave us at Liberty to diſ-believe Their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, when we ſee <hi>Their</hi> Practices.</p>
            <p>Again, the Endeavouring a Change is contrary to the duty of Praying for the ſafety of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, <note place="margin">Jer. 29, 7. Baruch 1, 11. 1 Tim: 2. 1, 2.</note> and the Proſperity of their Goverment a point which the <hi>Iews</hi> were commanded to do, for the Peace of <hi>Babilon,</hi> and the Lives of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> and <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tazar</hi> his Son, while they were Captives in that Place. And Chriſtians are Commanded to do the like for Kings and all that are in Authority under Them, that they may lead a quiet and peaceable life, in all Godlineſs and Honeſty, (with this Recommendation) becauſe its good and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in the ſight of God their Saviour: And which in the Firſt and pureſt Ages of Chriſtianity they form'd for their Emperours and Kings, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively to their Religion, <hi>Their Opinions in it,</hi> their Natural diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, or their Carriage towards them, for their Heathen Perſecutors, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> is a Competent Witneſs, <hi>Nos enim pro Salute Imperatorum
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192125:9"/> Deum in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>amus aternum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Dein oramus pro Ominius Imperatoribus, vitam illis Prolixam, Imperium Securum, Domum tutam, Exercitus fortes, Senatum Fidelem, Poputum Probum, Orbem quieium, &amp; quacunqn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inis &amp; Caeſaris vota ſunt;</hi> And ſo many <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dioni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uis, bulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Theodoret,</hi> &amp;c.</note> others Teſtify.</p>
            <p>To endeavour a Change, is moſt oppoſite to the tenour of the Goſpel, and the frame of Chriſtianity: The virtues That it inculcates, and This makes profeſſion of, are, Contentedneſs in all <hi>Eſtates;</hi> Humility in the higheſt, Patience in ſuffering, Meekneſs in bearing, and Charity in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving injuries: Whereas Diſcontent, Pride, Ambition, Impatience, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Revenge, are the Paſſions and Vices which inſtigate men to endeavour revolutions in Government.</p>
            <p>They affect Novelty, and therefore ſit uneaſy under the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which will be always deem'd heavy, by men of ſuch volatile and unquiet ſpirits. <hi>Militis aut pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bis ingenium obſervat. Nec impoſitos un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam cervice volen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rre duces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They love not a Conſtitution wherein Divine Providence hath an hand, and are for <hi>One of their Own ſetting up.</hi> This made the Iſraelites re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to have a King, like the reſt of the Nations round about, when they were under a <hi>Thescracy,</hi> God reſerving the Soveraignty in his own hands, but exerciſing the act of it by <hi>Samuel, 1 Sam.</hi> 8. 5.</p>
            <p>Or They are diſſatisfied with their ſtation and place in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as too low and mean for men of their abilities and merits; and ſuſpecting they are not like to riſe higher, or make themſelves greater, in the preſent poſture of affairs, are for diſturbing them, as the probableſt way to gain their point; or out of meer indignation to ſee themſelves neglected (as they eſteem) are for ſubverting it, tho they themſelves be oppreſt with its fall.</p>
            <p>Or if They ſtand high, they are diſpleas'd to ſee any above them, (for its the nature of Ambition not to look down, but up; not on thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, but thoſe before) and therefore they will unhinge the whole Frame, in hopes to get in their places; or tumble all down, ſo they may advance themſelves.</p>
            <p>Or <hi>They</hi> are Poor and Needy, and ſo would fain enrich themſelves, tho' it be with the ſpoil of their Countrey, which they can never come to Ranſack but in publick Commotions: Want engag'd <hi>Cateline</hi> and his Aſſociates. And thoſe in a Commonwealth who want Power or Riches will envy them who have; and out of meer anger or madneſs with their private Fortune, will deſire and Labour to have the Publick State turn'd Topſie turvy.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:192125:10"/> Or <hi>They</hi> like not the <note n="*" place="margin">or Religion</note> Diſpoſition of their Governors; They are too Mild or too Severe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Exceſſes of Princes are to be Born with, as we bear overmuch Drought, or Immoderate Rain; nor are vitious Princes always Succeeded by ſuch, but the good Interpoſe and compenſate for the bad; yet <hi>They</hi> will not expect time to aſſiſt them with this Remedy, but are for immediate diſcarding them, and going in gueſt of another of a more Sutable Temper, let the hazard of the Wild <hi>Gooſe</hi> chace be what it will; <hi>Ceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tacit. lieſt. l: 4. cap:</hi> 73: 74.</note> 
               <hi>ita loquitur, Quommodo Sterilitatem, aut nimios Imbres, &amp; catera naturae mala, ita Luxum vel Avaritiam dominaan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium tolerate, vitia erunt, donel homines, ſed neque hac continua &amp; meliorum interventu penſantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or <hi>They</hi> have been diguſted by them, becauſe in the diſpoſal of Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours they have paſſ'd them over, or have not had that High Eſteem for Them in words or actions: And to be Reveng'd for theſe neglects and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts, they will <hi>Combine</hi> to <hi>Depaſe</hi> or Murther Them; And care not whether they confound Heaven and Earth in one common Chaos again, ſo be it They have their Revenge. <hi>Pauſanius</hi> killed <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> for advancing <hi>Attalas</hi> to the Government of a Province, inſtead of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him upon his Complaint for abuſing his body; And <hi>Aruns</hi> brought the Goths into <hi>Italy,</hi> for having not Juſtice done him againſt <hi>Lucamon,</hi> who had defiled his Wife; <hi>Lucan</hi> Conſpired with <hi>Piſo</hi> and others againſt <hi>Nero</hi>'s life for ſuppreſſing his Poem; <hi>Quinctianus,</hi> for Defaming him in Song; <hi>Maximus</hi> againſt <hi>Valentinian</hi> the third. <hi>Iulian</hi> (a noble-man of <hi>Spain)</hi> calls in the <hi>Moors</hi> thither to be even with <hi>Roderic</hi> for corrupting his Wife or Daughter; and even he was, for their Succeſs put an end to his life, and the <hi>Gothique</hi> Race of Kings in that Country; <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Artois</hi> called the <hi>Engliſh</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> becauſe a Suit of Law went againſt him; and <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Bourbon</hi> Raiſ'd up <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth againſt <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt, for the ſame reaſon; and <hi>Bodilus</hi> killed <hi>Chilpherick</hi> for ordering him to be Whipt as a puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Or laſt of all their Villanies, have Render'd them Obnoxious to the Juſtice of the Government from which they have no way left of Saveing themſelves, unleſs by committing the greateſt, that of undermining and overthrowing it. The Philoſopher wiſely obſerv'd. Thoſe who have don wrong uſually fly to Sedition to protect them againſt puniſhment <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Ariſt <hi>Pol. l.</hi> 5. c. 3 And the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian ſaith, that Men fling themſelves into actual dangers, to ſecure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt thoſe they only fear, <hi>Imminentium periculum remedium ipſa
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:192125:10"/> pericula Arbitrati.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the methods which men uſually take to bring about a change are extreamly Ill. The firſt of which is the deviſing and venting Lyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Governors; And this of ſlandering <hi>Princes</hi> and their Conduct, is generally the firſt ſtep <hi>Seditious Incendiaries</hi> make in their progreſs to <hi>Rebellion. Abſolom</hi> began <hi>his</hi> Rebellion ſo, telling the <hi>People</hi> their mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were good and Right, but no man deputed of the <hi>King</hi> to hear them 2 <hi>Sam:</hi> 15. 34. In ſhort <hi>Wicked</hi> men Malliciouſly ſpy out Faults where there are none, Aggravate thoſe that are, and with alike greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and pleaſure divulge them both, to weaken his Credit and Eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with his people, They make invidious Conſtructions of his Deſigns; Odious Reflections on his Actions, and ſpread them abroad; which when they are grown the ſubject of common report, fill the Peoples minds with Fears and Jealouſies, and ſo diſpoſe them, as combuſtible matter ſoon takes fire, for Tumults and Inſurrections. The ſpreading of falſe Rumours is to the multitude as Windes to the Sea, makes them Rage and Swell, lift up their voice and Rore, in the Elegant Expreſſion of the Pſalmiſt. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 46. 3. who otherwiſe; like that, ſmooth when not blown upon, would have lain ſtill and calm: And by inſenſible degrees it tends to work this Effect, tho' the falſe news within few houres, dayes at fartheſt, can be diſprov'd, for either the Refutation ſhall never reach ſo far as the lye went, or if it doth, that hath made too deep an Impreſſion in <hi>Some</hi> to be eraſed; the Poyſon of it hath wrought it ſelf ſo far in, and lodg'd it ſelf ſo throughly, that <hi>Truth</hi> is too weak an <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote</hi> to Expell it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond method is near of kin to this; <hi>viz.</hi> Falſe and Hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call pretences. They who Levell at the Government, always diſguiſe thoſe <hi>Aims</hi> with the fair and ſpecious Colours of maintaining. Endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger'd <hi>Religion,</hi> Liberty and Property; while <hi>They</hi> have no ſenſe of the firſt, intend to oppreſs the ſecond and ſeiſe on the third; Theſe are all ſuch pleaſing names in the Peoples Ears, that albeit no attempt towards a change can be made, without firſt violating <hi>Religion</hi> and its Commands of <hi>Subjection</hi> and <hi>Obedience;</hi> And it is always ſeen if that ſucceeds, that Liberty is afterwards <hi>cruſh'd,</hi> and property <hi>uſurp'd: Yet</hi> as <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring Knaves</hi> never fail to make uſe of them; ſo nor <hi>Eaſy Fools</hi> to be charm'd and caught by them, and to contribute their aſſiſtance towards the diſtruction of them all in a change, for when that's Actualy come, then theſe cunning Contrivers of it are ſure to bind the ſilly, giddy hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of it forwards with <hi>Chains</hi> for Cords; and inſtead of an eaſy yoke
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:192125:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:192125:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:192125:12"/> to put an heavy burthenſome <hi>Clogg</hi> about their <hi>Necks;</hi> for <hi>Enjoy'd</hi> or <hi>Promis'd</hi> Freedom, to entayl <hi>Slabery</hi> on them and their <hi>Poſrerity:</hi> And And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave the <hi>Impudenceat</hi> the ſame time to call this <hi>State</hi> of Oppreſſion and Tyrany, an aſſerting the <hi>Privilidges</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> and Reſtoring the People to their <hi>Birthright</hi> as <hi>The Romans</hi> when they had <hi>Seiſed</hi> on <hi>Kingdoms without</hi> Right, and waſted them with <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Sword,</hi> call'd that deſolation Peace, <hi>Aufer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, trucidare, rapere falſis nominibus Imperium atque ubi ſolitudinem fecerint pacem appellan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Miſeriam ſervitutem falſo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem voca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent.</hi> This is the Recompence, and a deſerved one they meet with for their eaſineſs in believing the pretences, and forwardneſs in <hi>Aid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> them in their <hi>wicked</hi> Enterpriſes <hi>Abſolom</hi> us d both theſe <hi>Colours;</hi> He complai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d that the due courſe of Law was ſtop'd, and ſeem'd grieved that Juſtice did not freely flow in it's <hi>Channels,</hi> and promis'd withall to open them a paſſage, if he were made a Judge; <hi>That thery Man then who had a Suit, and would come unto him, ſhould have right done him,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. And <hi>yet He Uiolated</hi> the Law of <hi>Nature</hi> in thus <hi>affecting the Soveranity,</hi> which was not to be had without killing, <hi>Dethroning</hi> or <hi>Commanding His Father</hi> And did not <hi>Jeroboam</hi> cover his <hi>Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> at firſt with a <hi>Zeal</hi> for the purity of <hi>Religion?</hi> And when he had <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp'd</hi> the Throne did he not infringe the Peoples liberties, and lay Heavier <hi>Taxes</hi> on the <hi>Revolted</hi> Tribes, than ever <hi>Solomon</hi> did? towards the Payment of the <hi>Soldiers</hi> and <hi>Garriſons</hi> it was neceſſary he ſhould maintain for the holding of his <hi>Ill got Power;</hi> and thoſe no doubt har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be paid, in his <hi>Divided</hi> and unquiet <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> than the ſame would have been under <hi>Solomon</hi> while the Kingdom ſtood <hi>En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and his Reign flowed with <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Wealth</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third method is <hi>Steaking through all Oaths</hi> they ſtand bound by, of bearing <hi>True faith</hi> and <hi>Allegiance</hi> to their Gove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nours; of diſcovering all <hi>Treaſonable</hi> Deſignes and Practices againſt their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or Authority: Oaths in which <hi>They</hi> depoſited with them the Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt pawn it was poſſible for them to ſtake down, and gave them the Strongeſt Security the others could Require of <hi>Their</hi> Fidelity and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>viz. Their Salvation;</hi> Oaths in which <hi>They</hi> call'd God's Omniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to witneſs their Engagements, and his Juſtice and Power to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge <hi>The breath</hi> of them. <hi>And yet,</hi> as if <hi>They</hi> were no more to be held by them than <hi>Samſon</hi> was with green wyths or new Ropes; Or as if <hi>Their</hi> Conſcieuces were no more to be wounded by <hi>Perjury</hi> than the <hi>German</hi> Hard-men are by <hi>Sword</hi> and <hi>Sho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> or laſt of all, as if <hi>They</hi> had a ſecret Receipe of being acquainted with <hi>Conſpiracies,</hi> and not being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the <hi>Treaſon</hi> of them.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:192125:12"/>
            <p>But if there were no breaking through <hi>Oaths,</hi> (and yet I believe there is ſcarce any form of Regiment in the world which takes not this kind oſ cautionary Bond from their Subjects) they muſt make <hi>Their</hi> way through all Natural Obligations to come at their end: for every man who is not born to Empire, antecedent to all Oaths and abſtracting from the Force of all Humane Laws, is born with a Tye of duty and Obedience to the Government under which he was born; And he can no more Diſolve change or Tranſfer this <hi>Obligation by a ſubſequent Protectation</hi> of his Obedience to a <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> other than <hi>His Natural,</hi> than he could before he came into the World chooſe of what Parents he would deſcend the Country where, and the dominion under which he would make his Entrance into it.</p>
            <p>And now ſuppoſe The Treaſon meet with all the <hi>Succeſs</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators could wiſh, <hi>yet theſe Perſons</hi> are oft, at the long Run, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by vengeance, and exemplary puniſh'd in this World. Innumer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Footſteps of this Juſtice are left <hi>Us,</hi> ſtanding both on Sacred and Civil Records: The Earth opened her Mouth wide and ſwallow'd up <hi>Corah Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> with their Rebellious Crew in the very Act and Height of <hi>Their</hi> wickedneſs: <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milech,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Judges 9. 53.</note> who dy'd his Princely Scarlet in the <hi>Blood</hi> of Seventy Brethren he ſlew that he might Rule without Controul, had his <hi>Skull</hi> at the ſtorming of <hi>Thebez</hi> broke by a ſtone thrown by a Womans hand, on which the Hiſtorian, who Relates it, makes this Remark. <hi>Athaliah</hi> who Murther'd all the Royal <note place="margin">2. Kings: 11. 16.</note> Line of <hi>Judah</hi> (except an Infant He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r preſerv'd by his <hi>Aunt for a more fabourable Iuncture)</hi> that ſhe might Reign, and Reign without a Rival, fell from her greatneſs by the ſame <hi>Bloody</hi> ſteps ſhe mounted to it; was ſlain by her Guard within the Verge of her Palace: <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the grand <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> of the <note place="margin">1. Kings: 15. 19.</note> the <hi>Iſralitiſh</hi> Crown, tho'he eſcap'd in his perſon yet was puniſh'd in the utter Extirpation of his Poſterity; <hi>Nadab</hi> his Son kill'd and all his Family by the <hi>Sword</hi> of <hi>Baaſha,</hi> not one left alive who breath'd. This Murtherer's <note place="margin">1. Kings: 10. 12.</note> Son <hi>Elah,</hi> together with all the Male Line were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd by <hi>Zimri;</hi> not one left who piſs'd againſt the <note place="margin">1. Kings: 16: 15. 18.</note> Wall, <hi>Zimri</hi> after ſeven days Reign, lay'd hands on himſelf to avoid falling into <hi>Om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'s</hi> who beſieged him, Burning his Palace over his own head <hi>Shallum</hi> who tooke away <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hariah's</hi> life and Kingdom, was <note place="margin">1. Kings. 15. 30.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:192125:13"/> depriv'd of both within a Month by <hi>Menahem,</hi> whoſe Son <hi>Pekajah</hi> had the like turn done him by <hi>Pekah</hi> the Captain of his Guard, and he by <hi>Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hea,</hi> who in the <hi>9th</hi> year of <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings:</hi> 18. 9.</note> his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> was ſtrip'd of his Regallity, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Captive by <hi>Salmanezer</hi> into <hi>Aſſiria</hi> and <hi>Media,</hi> and with him expir'd that M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>narchy.</p>
            <p>And ſhould I Travel out of ſacred Story into Prophane for inſtances, Time would faile me in recounting the Tragical Ends of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers</hi> or Regicides of <hi>Cyrns</hi> who Seiſed on his Grandfathers Kingdoms; of <hi>Beſſus</hi> whoſe Murther of <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius Ochus</hi> cauſed the Tranſlation of the Empire from the <hi>Perſian</hi> to the <hi>Greeks;</hi> of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hillip</hi> the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> of the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Crown, ſlain between his Son <hi>Alexander</hi> the great and his Son in Law <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Epicus,</hi> at the Eſpouſal of his Daughter, of <hi>Piſiſtratus</hi> who <hi>Invaded</hi> the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>henian; Julius Caeſar</hi> who Invaded the <hi>Roman</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: The Murderers of <hi>Gordian</hi> the Emperour, who fell all by <hi>Their</hi> own hands, uſing thoſe very Swords againſt their own lives, which <hi>They</hi> had before Imployed to take away others. And Infinite Numbers more mentioned by the Roman <hi>Byzantine</hi> and other Writers; only I can't o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit two Memorable Examples, the one of <hi>Maximus,</hi> who procur'd the Murther of <hi>Valanttnian</hi> the third, Torn afterwards in Peices by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Rome;</hi> the other of <hi>Phocas,</hi> who through the Barbarous murther of his maſter <hi>Mauritius,</hi> Aſcended the Throne of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> he taken by <hi>Pho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inus</hi> received a ſuitable Reward, and had his Head, Hands and Feet with his Privities cut off:</p>
            <p>In theſe (Generally ſpeaking) is that ſaying of our Saviour verified, <hi>They</hi> who take the Sword, (take it againſt Lawfull Authority) ſhall Periſh with the Sword, (the Sword of Juſtice) And of St. <hi>John, he that killeth with the Sword, muſt be killed with the Sword;</hi> ſo <hi>David</hi> Killed the <hi>Amalekite</hi> who ſlew <hi>Saul</hi> at his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>treaty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And can it be thought, that he who <hi>Will not hold him Guiltleſs that taketh his name</hi> in vain, ſhould connive at the violation of all <hi>Obligations</hi> of Duty and Fidelity <hi>contracted</hi> in that name; and let <hi>ſuch</hi> eſcape Scot-free that riſe up againſt them who wear his name, and are clad in the Rayes of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie; That if men ſhall be in danger of Hell fire for calling their Brother Fool, ſhall <hi>They</hi> be in none for Rayling againſt their Superiors inveſted with <hi>Authority</hi> from above, and <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet. 1. 2. comp. with the 10. Iud. 8. comp.</hi> with the 13.</note> 
               <hi>Acting by a Commiſſion from heaven?</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Iude,</hi> have taught <hi>Us</hi> otherwiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That God Reſerveth <hi>Such</hi> who ſpeak evil of <hi>Dignities</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:192125:13"/> unto the day of <hi>Judgment,</hi> to be puniſhed; for the Blackneſs of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for ever.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Lyars, Sorcerers, Whoremongers, Murtherers</hi> and <hi>Idolaters,</hi> ſhall receive their part in the Lake which <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 8.</note> Burneth with <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Brimſtone,</hi> as we are infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m'd they ſhall; ſurely <hi>ſuch Lyars,</hi> who Maliciouſly Slander <hi>Their prince</hi> firſt to weaken his Credit, then his Hands; ſuch <hi>Sorcerers,</hi> who with the Witchcraft of Cunning and Fair Speaking, alienate the Peoples Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from <hi>him; ſuch Whoremongers</hi> who are Guilty of, and ſtand anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Juſtice for all the <hi>Rapes</hi> and <hi>Deſtorations Soldiers</hi> rais'd by <hi>Them</hi> to begin an Inſurrection, and <hi>make</hi> a <hi>Revolt,</hi> in the heat of <hi>War</hi> and Luſt commit, ſurely then <hi>thoſe Murtherers</hi> of their honeſt fellow Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, who will not ſide with them in taking up Arms; Then <hi>Thoſe Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters;</hi> who Crown'd with Succeſs erect a <hi>Falſe Power</hi> in oppoſition to the <hi>Legal One and would Compell all to acknowledge and pay Homage</hi> to it, like <hi>Nibuchadnezzar,</hi> to fall down and worſhip the <hi>Image, They</hi> have made and <hi>Set up,</hi> ſhall be caſt there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some</hi> there are who have (too lately) made uſe of <hi>Their</hi> pretended Fear of God, to Juſtle out the King's Honour; their ſerving God, to excuſe <hi>theſe</hi> diſobedience to the <hi>King;</hi> their fits of Devotion &amp; Extatical Raptures, their <hi>Acts of Diſloyalty, Their Aſſerting the True Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Juſtifying their Riſing up againſt his Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now let every <hi>Engliſhman</hi> begin to examin himſelf, whether he hath not <hi>medled with them</hi> who were given to <hi>change?</hi> Have not You ſhew'd your ſelves ſuch, by ſiding and going along with that Faction which wrought the <hi>laſt diſmal change,</hi> or by following men who Trac'd their ſteps, and Practic'd the ſame methods of Sedition, which usher'd in that Rebellion? did you not greedily Swallow down the Calumnies and and Slanders <hi>They</hi> F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d you with againſt the Government? Have you their perſons in the greateſt Admiration, who made the Biggeſt Noiſe for Religion and Liberty, while <hi>Their</hi> Lives manifeſted they had extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd the one, all but the Name, and <hi>Their Arbitrary</hi> proceedings that they were Reſolv'd to Proſtitute the other to their own Luſts? ſuch who had Scrupl'd at Order and Decency in the <hi>Church,</hi> but had made none of involving three Kingdoms in Miſery and Confuſion; ſtrein'd at Conformity, but Swallow'd down <hi>Rebellion;</hi> ſlumbl'd at a Ceremony, but leap'd over the Murther <hi>(or Dethroning)</hi> of <hi>Their King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And after all this, did you not look upon your ſelves as abſolv'd from the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and on them as antiquated Bonds?
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:192125:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:192125:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:192125:15"/> Or were you not for expounding Them ſo as they might be beſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated to <hi>Rebellion,</hi> or willing <hi>Disciples</hi> of ſuch Maſters who did? That they were ſtipulations of a Conditional Obedience, Provided the King maintained your Rights, and that limitted and Reſtrain'd to ſome Caſe only; ſo that the King not performing the former, you were not bound to the latter; or Commanding ſomething without the Verge of his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, might be oppos'd <hi>by Arms,</hi> and Forc'd within compaſs; Or that thoſe Sacred Tyes might be violated without Sin, for promoting ſuch great Goods as the Power of Godlineſs and the Freedom of the Goſpell! did not the Casuiſtical Divinity of ſuch Rabbies pleaſe you, who directed You, in Order to ſhake the Crown from off the Monarch's head, to break any Oath with the deepeſt ſence of <hi>Religion,</hi> which you before had Sworn with a Sound Conſcience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And beſides the Wickedneſs of Breaking Through Theſe Sacred Obligations have you not bound your ſelves by illegal <hi>Aſſociations</hi> or Covenants (directly oppoſite to theſe ſolemn engagements) to labour a change? So <hi>Cataline</hi> initiated his Complices to the privacy of his conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, by a Sacrament ſolemn as a Sacrifice to the Gods, He drank to Them in a mingl'd bowl of man's blood and wine, and made them pledge him and one another in that, and ſo doing their mutual Faith, devoting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with horrid execrations to ſuffer all Ills, in caſe they infring'd it, afore he ventur'd to acquaint them with the villany they were to be actors in. And if you have in any of the forementioned reſpects been guilty (as it is more than to be ſuſpected you have.) Let me exhort you, to waſh away the contracted guilt with the tears of repentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Nott,</hi> at the <hi>Queen's Arms</hi> in the <hi>Pall Mall.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:192125:15"/>
            <head>A Sermon Entituled, <hi>Some ſeaſonable Reflections on the Diſcovery of the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Plot,</hi> By William Sherlock D. D.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſal. 18. Verſe 50.</bibl>
               <q>Great deliverance giveth he to his King, and ſheweth mercy to his Annointed, to <hi>David,</hi> and to his ſeed for evermore.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>MEn of turbulent and reſtleſs ſpirits will be ſure to find, or make ſome pretences or occaſions of quarrel under the moſt juſt and equal Government. Sometimes <hi>They diſpute the right of Succeſſion;</hi> but this they could not do in <hi>David</hi>'s caſe, unleſs they would diſpute God's right to place and diſplace Princes: For he was immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately choſen by God, and annointed by his Prophet, and yet this could not ſecure him from Conſpiracies and Rebellions.</p>
            <p>Others pretend great Oppreſſion and male-adminiſtration of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, tho' <hi>Their</hi> licentious noiſes and clamours ſufficiently confute it; for men who are moſt oppreſt dare ſay the leaſt of it. And <hi>Others</hi> make Religion a pretence for <hi>Their</hi> Rebellion; Religion! the greateſt and the deareſt intereſt of all: But methinks it is a dangerous way for Men to rebel to ſave <hi>Their Souls,</hi> when God has <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 2.</note> threatned damnation againſt <hi>Thoſe</hi> who rebel: But this is a vain pretence, for no man can fight for Religion, who has any Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Religion is a quiet, peaceable, governable thing; it teaches <hi>Men to ſuffer patiently,</hi> but never to rebel. And were there any true concernment for Religion in this pretence, can We imagine, that the <hi>moſt profeſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts;</hi> the moſt lewd proſtigate <hi>Wretches,</hi> the greateſt <hi>Prodigies and Monſters of wickedneſs,</hi> ſhould be ſo zealous for Religion? But it's evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:192125:16"/> it is not Religion ſuch men are zealous for, but a liberty in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; that is, that every one may have his liberty to be of any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or of none; which ſerves the Atheiſts turn, as well as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sectaries; but is nor much for the honour or intereſt of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe no man doubts how many dangers a Prince is expos'd to who flies before an enrag'd and victorious enemy: A Prince whoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was murther'd, and himſelf forc'd into baniſhment by his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects! Who knows not whither to go, where to hide himſelf, whom to truſt: Many perſons who were in greateſt power, being concern'd (for their own preſervation) to keep Him out; while thoſe who wiſh'd Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Return, durſt not whiſper any thing tending to call the King back again. This was the condition of our dread Soveraign, who was hunted as: Partridge in the mountains, purſued by his own rebellious Subjects, who had uſurp'd his Throne, and thirſted after his Blood. But then God found an hiding place for Him, and delivered Him from the deſire and expectation of his Enemies: And, as the Pſalmiſt ſays, <hi>This is the Lords doing; and it is marvellous in our eyes;</hi> now know We, that the Lord <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth his Annointed, He will hear Him from his holy Heaven, with the ſaving ſtrength of his right hand,</hi> Pſal. 65. 7.</p>
            <p>God may ſometimes ſuffer Treaſon and Rebellion to be proſperous, but it can never proſper but when God pleaſeth; and it is impoſſible Rebels ſhould ever know that. There is nothing more expreſly contrary to the reveal'd will of God, than Treaſonable Plots and Conſpiracies againſt Soveraign Princes: And tho God does many times <hi>permit thoſe things to be done, which he has forbid to be done,</hi> or elſe no man could ever be guilty of any ſin; yet his forbidding of it is a plain argument that he does not approve it, that he will not countenance it. God never indeed interpoſes by an irreſiſtible power to hinder men from chooſing <hi>that which is wicked,</hi> for he offers no force or violence to mens wills: but when this wickedneſs is injurious to others, who are the objects of his care and providence, he many times interpoſes to prevent the miſchief. Who ever ſuſpected, that the Fire at <hi>New-Market,</hi> was ſent by God for the preſervation of our King and His Royal Brother?</p>
            <p>Chriſtian Religion is the greateſt ſecurity of Government both i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> its precepts and examples: It commands <hi>Every Soul to be ſubject to the higher Powers,</hi> and threatens <hi>eternal damnation againſt Rebels;</hi> it ſtrictly enjoyns the practice of all ſociable virtues, and charms thoſe boiſterous paſſions which diſturb humane converſation; it requires Us to obey our Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:192125:16"/> in all lawful things, and quietly to ſubmit and ſuffor, when we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> obey: And the bleſſed Jeſus, who was the Author of our Religion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our great Pattern and Example, did himſelf practiſe theſe laws, which he gave to <hi>US.</hi> He liv'd in obedience to the Civil Power, and though the Jewiſh Nation, which was a free People, the Lot and Inheritance of God himſelf, were then in ſubjection to the <hi>Romans,</hi> yet He would not give Them the leaſt encouragement to ſhake off the yoke, but commands them to <hi>give unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſar's, <hi>and unto God the things that are God</hi>'s. He died himſelf upon the Croſs, and made this the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of our diſcipleſhip, To <hi>take up our Croſs and follow Him;</hi> and thus the Apoſtles and Primitive Chriſtians did, they chearfully follow'd their Maſter to the Croſs, and conquered by ſuffering. Chriſtianity was plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the world by no other arts but the fooliſhneſs Preaching, and it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended it ſelf <hi>Only,</hi> by a reſolute and patient ſuffering for the name of Chriſt. This is the true temper and ſpirit of Chriſtianity. Under the moſt barbarous and perſecuting Emperors, <hi>no Chriſtian ever ſuffer'd as a Rebel,</hi> They gave no other diſturbance to the Government, than by confeſſing themſelves to be Chriſtians, and ſuffering for it. Their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers indeed were very formidable, but nothing elſe; for in imitation of their great Maſter, <hi>They went as lambs to the ſlaughter, and as ſheep before their ſhearers are dumb, ſo they opened not their mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding this, our daily experience tells <hi>US,</hi> that when Religion is divided into Factions and Parties, or rather Men are divided into Factions and Parties upon account of Religion, there is nothing more imbitters mens ſpirits againſt each other, nor gives greater diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance to publick Government. <hi>All the Troubles and Miſeries which for theſe late years have overwhelmed this unfortunate Iſland have been dooing to this cauſe;</hi> Religion has been made either the reaſon or the pretence of all.</p>
            <p>To deny that <hi>Proſeſt Proteſtants</hi> have ever rebell'd againſt their Prince, is to deny, that there ever was a Civil War in <hi>England.</hi> And I would to God, <hi>We</hi> had but one inſtance of this; it might have left ſome hope ſtill, that This was not the temper nor the <hi>Principles of the Men,</hi> but ſome unlucky <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>cture of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffairs, which tranſported <hi>Them</hi> beyond the bounds of their Duty, and their own <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ow'd Principles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When Religion turns into a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to curb and reſtrain, and quell ſuch pretences, is not to invade the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Conſcience, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of Religion,</hi> but to ſecure the publick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to prevent the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of new Rebellions. And no ſob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> man can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Prince for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:192125:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:192125:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:192125:18"/> this, tho he may <hi>Thoſe,</hi> (and ought to expreſs a juſt indignation againſt Them) who forfeit this liberty, by abuſing it for a cloak of maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>A great and paſſionate Zeal, like a diſtemper'd Love, blinds mens eyes, and makes them miſtake both their Enemies and Friends. It fills their heads with endleſs jealouſies and fears, and makes them ſtart and run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from their own ſhadow. Such a boyſterous Zeal is the frenzy and Calenture of Religion, which makes men uncapable of any ſober coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and all prudent Reſolves, and precipitates them into the moſt wild, extravagant, and <hi>irreligious attempts.</hi> There is nothing more perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious than Zeal, when it gets a-head, and bears down all the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Reaſon and Religion before it. When men are conſcious to themſelves, that they are engag'd in a good cauſe, and have honeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, it makes them more bold and venturous: For tho few men da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> own it, yet the actions of too many ſufficiently proclaim, that <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> think they may ſtrain a Point,</hi> and diſpence with ſtrict Duty, when it is to ſerve a good cauſe, when the Honour of God, and the Intereſt of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is concern'd: Such a Zeal does violently puſh Men forward, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> does not ſteer well, nor obſerve its compaſs; and thus it is too often ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that Men who begin with a zeal for Religion, inſenſibly ſlip into Stat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Factions, and <hi>are engag'd vaſtly beyond what They firſt deſign'd.</hi> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Us</hi> then above all things have a care of our Zeal, that we may not miſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en earthly Fire, which burns and conſumes, for that divine and harmle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Flame, which is kindled at God's altar. A true zeal for Religion, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more nor leſs: than ſuch an hearty love for it as makes us very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in the practiſe of it out ſelves, and contented, if God ſees it fit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lay down our lives for it, and very induſtrious to promote the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and practiſe of Religion in the World, by all lawful and prude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> means. A true Chriſtian Zeal will not ſuffer <hi>US</hi> to tranſgreſs the ſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bounds of our duty to God, or of our duty to Men, eſpecially to King and Princes, whatever <hi>Flattering Proſpect</hi> of advantage it may give. To lye, to forſwear our ſelves, to hate and revile each other; To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and libel Governors in Church or State; to ſtir up, or counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, with the leaſt Thought, any Plots, Seditions or Rebellions again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the King, <hi>is not a Zeal for God nor for Religion:</hi> for this <hi>wiſdom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not from above, but is earthly, ſenſual, and devilliſh: for where strife and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is, there is every evil work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let <hi>Our paſt Experience</hi> therefore teach Us, to watch over the lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:192125:18"/> ſtirrings, and firſt appearances of a ſeditious and factious ſpirit, either in our ſelves or others, however it may be <hi>diſguiſed with a pretence of Religion.</hi> Faction, like other vices, has but very ſmall beginnings; but when thoſe beginnings are indulg'd, it ſoon improves, and gets ſtrength. <hi>Omne in praecipiti vitium ſtetit:</hi> When men once eſpouſe a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, like thoſe who are running down hill; they cannot ſtop when they pleaſe. Diſcontents and jealouſies are eaſily fomented, when <hi>We</hi> have once given admiſſion to them; and the buſy Factors and Agents for Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, when <hi>They</hi> find <hi>US</hi> never ſo little diſpoſed to receive the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, uſe their utmoſt art and skill, all the methods of inſinuation and addreſs, to make us Proſelytes. I doubt not but <hi>many Men</hi> have died Rebels, and ſuffer'd as Traytors, who at firſt did as much abhor the though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of Treaſon and Rebellion, as any of us can; Thus I doubt not but it was in our late Troubles; And <hi>thus I believe it is at this Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let ſuch Examples as theſe make <hi>Us</hi> wary, how <hi>We</hi> begin to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, or to whiſper our diſcontents and fears; how we begin to liſten to be ſuſpicious of our Prince, or of his Government; and to hear with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, any ſcandalous ſtories or reflections on either. Thoſe who can with content and pleaſure hear their Prince and his Government revil'd, will ſoon think him not fit to be <hi>Their</hi> King.</p>
            <p>And the great danger of ſuch beginnings is, that <hi>We</hi> are not apt to obſerve them in our ſelves or others, when Religion is concern'd in the quarrel. <hi>We</hi> think it all Zeal, pure Zeal! and can't ſuſpect our ſelves or others, to be in any danger of turning Rebels. But whatever is in its own nature a degree or tendency towards Rebellion, is ſo where-ever, and <hi>in whomſoever</hi> it is found; and there is always more danger, that the beginnings of vice ſhould corrupt the beſt temper of mind, than any hope that a ſound and religious diſpoſition ſhould correct the malign in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of ſuch a vice. Some mens Religion does as much incline them to Faction, as ſecular intereſt doth other men; and there is no ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Faction, as that which is bred and nouriſh'd by the corruptions of Religion. The Jewiſh Zealots, and the Chriſtian Enthuſiaſts of <hi>all ſorts,</hi> are too plain an Example of it. And therefore when men, who make great pretences to Religion, begin to talk or act factiouſly, a fair opportunity is as like to make them Rebels, as any other men. Thus <hi>We</hi> often ſee it is, and this is a ſufficient reaſon to ſuſpect all ſuch begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, either in our ſelVes or others, whatever <hi>glorious pretences</hi> we may have.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Baſſet</hi> at the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:192125:19"/>
            <head>The Power of Kings from GOD. A SERMON Preach'd, at <hi>Sarum,</hi> By <hi>Paul Lathom,</hi> Prebendary there.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Prov. 8. 15.</bibl>
               <q>By Me Kings Reign.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>KIngs have their Authority deriv'd immediately from God, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Authority is not confer'd on Them, as a Truſt by the People. <hi>Let us</hi> conſider firſt what Titles the Scriptures give to King They are called the Miniſters of God, therefore not of men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1, 4. 6. The Powers that be, are ſaid to be Ordained of God, therefore not of Men. <hi>v. i</hi> for the queſtion concerning St. <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it from Heaven? or of Men? ſeems to put this upon an Iſſue; Beſides they are call'd <hi>Elohim,</hi> Earthly Gods, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 82, 6. And <hi>what Peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can make there own Gods, without Palpable Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When God firſt Subjected his own People, <hi>Iſrael</hi> to the Government of Kings, the People had nothing to do in conferring the Power <hi>Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was made their Ruler immediately by God ſo <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> and the <hi>Iudge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for ſo long the Theocracy did continue viſable among them. When th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> People deſir'd a King with formality, God is not angry with them ſimp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for deſiring a King; for he foretold their having a King, and gave hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> directions for his Government, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17 but for ſome irregularities their manner of deſiring him, But how was he choſen? not by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but by <hi>Lot. 1, Sam:</hi> 10, 20, 21. the determination whereof from the Lord, <hi>Prov:</hi> 16. 33. <hi>no hand of the People in chooſing him David</hi> was made King by God's immediate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sam:</hi> 16. 1. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:192125:19"/> the Theocracy ſeems to end. Afterward the Government did deſcend by Succeſſion And <hi>Thoſe</hi> that pretend directions <hi>from</hi> the Scripture in every thing, will be at a loſs where to finde directions there for the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to take away or Confer Power upon their Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We</hi> Challenge any man from Prophane Hiſtories, to ſhew <hi>Us</hi> any Footſteps of ſuch beginings of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> when the People did intruſt this Power to their King? If they acknowledge that their Hiſtory fails them, let not alſo reaſon fail them; <hi>Let not Loyalty fail Them;</hi> let not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience fail them let them have ſomhing more than bold Surmiſes, or elſe not attempt to build a Suppoſition of ſuch dangerous conſequence, upon the meer ſtrength of imagination.</p>
            <p>If therefore they Perſiſt and Urge <hi>Us</hi> to ſhew, how Monarchy firſt came to Subject men to Obedience, I think the Hiſtory of the <hi>Bible</hi> will give <hi>US</hi> light enough. That <hi>Patriarchal</hi> Government, or the Ruling of the Father or eldeſt of the Family over the Reſt, was the firſt form of Government in the World, I think is generaly own'd; Now when the Families increaſed, the Subjects multiplied, and by inſenſible degrees the <hi>Patriarchal</hi> Government ſeems to have ſetled into that Government of the Reguli, or ſmall Kings, which was upon the matter the ſame; when <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> Conquered the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which is leſs in extent than the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> alone, he found and Subdued 31 Kings, <hi>Ioſh:</hi> 12, 24. And it ſeems this was the leaſt Jurisdiction of their Reguli. For after him <hi>Iudg: 1. 7. Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ibezek</hi> when he was Conquer'd, doth own that he kept 70 Reguli in Barbarous Servitude under him. And ſome Hundreds of years after the King of <hi>Syria</hi> (no great Prince) had 32 Kings at once in his Army, 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 20. 1. ſo that it ſeems their Territories and power were then ſurely but an inconſiderable alteration of <hi>External</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that which by degrees introduced greater Monarchy's.</p>
            <p>If <hi>We</hi> further proceed to take a view of all the ways, whereby <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> aſcend to the Throne, it will appear they are but few; and that in none of thoſe the People confer the power on the <hi>King;</hi> firſt by D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcent or Succeſſion, as in <hi>England:</hi> Now <hi>who can ſay that the People herecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Power?</hi> If they ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d that at the Kings Coronation the conſent of the People is demanded; it is evident that the King is King to all intents and purpoſes before his Coronation, Beſides neither are all the People Sommon'd, nor any conſiderable part of them appear at a Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: And if then thereſhould be any ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly <hi>Sheba,</hi> that ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject his <hi>Prince,</hi> that would not hinder the Coronation, ſo that this is but barely a thing of courſe and <hi>doth not deſide the King's Power from
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:192125:20"/> the People at all.</hi> Secondly thoſe that attain a Crown by conqueſt, no man can ſay They expect or receive the explicit conſent of the People, tho' a tacit conſequential conſent may be argued in their yeilding him a forc'd obedience, Thirdly <hi>Thoſe that Surpriſe a Throne by Fraud,</hi> tho' they may impoſe upon the People ſo as to gain a formal conſent. Yet is there no real conſent in thoſe that are thus bewitch'd or cajol'd, Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, there are ſome that come to a Crown by Elcteion: And here our Male-contents think they are ſecure, that They derive their Power from the People. But we muſt conſider the <hi>great difference</hi> that is betwixt Deſigning the perſon, and conferring the Power; The former is from thoſe that chooſe Him, the latter by no meanes, the Dean and Chapiter of a Cathedral, by the Kings leave) chooſe a Biſhop <hi>(Sede vacante)</hi> this choice deſigns the perſon, but doth not confer the Power, which is after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards given him in his conſecration The <hi>Aldermen</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> of a City, do yearly chooſe their Mayor; this choice doth indeed deſigne the perſon, but not confer the power, which deſcends by virtue of the Kings Charter, So when the ſeven Electors chooſe an Emperour of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> or thoſe that uſually chooſe a King in <hi>Poland,</hi> they only deſign the perſon; his Power is not from them, but immediatly from God. And now, whether the Power of Kings be ſo immediatly ſubordinate to God and depending upon Him, that no <hi>Earthly: ower</hi> whatſoever can call them to account for the Adminiſtration of their Government, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their Truſt?</p>
            <p>The Accountableneſs of Princes to the People in their Repreſentatives hath <hi>paſſed (too lately) for currant Doctrine</hi> in the days of impriſoning King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That Reaſon and Conſcience may be ſatisfied of the falſneſs and dangerousneſs of ſuch Aſſertions, I ſhall offer what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, to prove that God Almighty is the only Ruler of <hi>Princes,</hi> and that to him only they owe their accounts, firſt in reaſon it is a contradiction, after <hi>We</hi> have own'd the King to be Supreme in all Cauſes, and over all Perſons both <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> and <hi>Civil,</hi> to affirm afterwards, that there is any other Power that hath Right to call <hi>him</hi> to an account, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently is in that reſpect his ſuperior. That <hi>We</hi> have own'd the King as Supreme, I ſuppoſe all men will confeſs, and the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls him ſo, 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2, 13. And that his accountableneſs to any other on Earth, would render theſe perſons that may demand his account <hi>(to nomine)</hi> Superiour to Him, is grounded upon that known maxim, <hi>Par in parem nou habet poteſtatem.</hi> If therefore the King be Supreme, and yet hath others on Earth that are Superiour to him, then is he Supreme, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:192125:20"/> not Supreme, a palpable contradiction, both branches of which cannot be true. Now the Kings Supremacy, both the Law hath Setled, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>Good Subject</hi> hath own'd, and therefore muſt diſown the Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the People, either Collectively, or in their Repreſentative as a Spurious Offspring deſcended from <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis minor.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, If <hi>We</hi> conſult the Scriptures, when <hi>David</hi> had committed thoſe two great ſins of Adultery and Murther, either of which ſingly was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital by the Jewiſh laws, yet do we not find him call'd to account for them, but only by the great King of Kings, who takes the matter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his own hands, ſends his Prophet to him, Summons him before him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as his Judge, brings him to Repentance, accepts his Confeſſion, and Remits his Treſpaſs, as to the Eternal puniſhment. And <hi>David</hi> appears very ſenſible of his being accountable to God only; when in his moſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent Confeſſion he crys out againſt Thee, Thee! only have I Sinned, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51, 3. If therefore <hi>We</hi> own the Scriptures for our guid in all doubtfull and important points, here is an inſtance to guide <hi>Us</hi> in a matter of this great and weighty Moment.</p>
            <p>Thirdly to hold a Power in the People to call the <hi>Prince</hi> to account for the Adminiſtration of his Government is moſt highly inconſiſtent with the law of nature, and all the Reaſon and Conſcience immaginable: For it makes the People at once the complainants, the witneſſes, the <hi>Jury</hi> and the <hi>Judge,</hi> For when we ſpeak of the King, and the People, they are but two parties. If therefore the King muſt be impleaded, who muſt be the Complanants &amp; Proſecutors? the People! who Witneſſes? the People! who muſt be the <hi>Jury</hi> to enquire of matter of Fact? the People! who muſt be the <hi>Iudge,</hi> to determin he hath broken a Law, and be obnoxious to pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the People! at laſt when Sentence is paſſed upon him, who muſt Execute it? ſtill the People! a thing never heard of in any Judicial proceedings, even in the moſt Barbarous Nations: and that which muſt needs preclude the doing of Juſtice, when paſſion or intereſt in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile, would carry all things according to their own Luſts and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</p>
            <p>The Judgments of God, have dogg'd at the Heels, in all Ages, <hi>Thoſe Subjects</hi> that have Riſen up in <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt their Lawfull King, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ther Secretly, or openly, taken away their Lives Had <hi>Zimri</hi> peace who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w his maſter? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And how hath the Juſtice of God, become the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger of Blood, and purſued Thoſe, who had killed and taken poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and boaſted of their Wickedneſs, for ſeveral years together; and ſome of them deſired it might be written on their Tombs, <hi>here li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sens
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:192125:21"/> of the late Kings Iudges.</hi> This I hope will not be forgotten in <hi>This Generation, &amp;c.</hi> That all men may hear and fear, and <hi>do no more ſo Preſumptiouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If Kings then have their Power from God, and are not accountable to any perſon or perſons on Earth, then is it a great Sin, to Arraign the wiſdom or Juſtice of his Majeſties proceedings, in the <hi>Convention</hi> of men of unſanctified Hearts, unhallow'd lives and prophane Mouths. <hi>Too many</hi> now adays make it either a ſign of Grace, or a token of Wiſdom, or at leaſt an argument of good affections to the publick, to <hi>Slander the Footſteps of God's Anointed;</hi> And as if they would inveſtigate their Pedegrees, from <hi>Cora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and his Complices, do proceed by Riſing up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> reproaching both Prince and Prieſt, as if They took too much upon them. If he that ſtept out of his rank, without allowance of his Officer, to fight an Enemy, though he kill'd him, was condemn'd for deſerting his place, what cenſure can be great enough for <hi>Thoſe</hi> that deſert their Ranks and Stations, not to fight an Enemy (a Forreign Invader,) but <hi>to encounter their lawful Soveraign?</hi> If God Almighty be the <hi>only Ruler of Princes,</hi> and neither the People collective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nor Repreſentatively; have power to cenſure the actions of a King, then certainly the Individuals, or little knots of the Popul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cy, have much leſs power to cenſure his proceedings.</p>
            <p>When Men preſume to think that the King is the peoples creature, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving his Power as a Truſt from them; and when the fondneſs and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty of the notion by degrees hath flatter'd them into a fix'd opinion of it, They will quickly implead his Authority, as a conditional and preca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious thing, and upon the leaſt diſtaſte, will be tempted to meditate a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of their truſt; So that what does not jump with one mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, tho it may advance anothers, the King muſt anſwer for; And what does not indulge the luſts of the fooliſh, though 'tis highly accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Wiſe, the King muſt account for; ſo apt are <hi>Reſty Men</hi> to clamour againſt the Settlements of their own ſecurity and happineſs, and promote the ſteps of their own ruine and confuſion. But when Men ſhall ſeriouſly conſider that the Sword is put into His hand by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and that he bears it not in vain, that he is a Revenger to <hi>execute wrath upon Him that doth evil Rom.</hi> 13. 1. This will oblige them to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and loyalty to their earthly Soveraign, out of a principle of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards the King of Heaven; This will ſpeak them at once both <hi>True Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Good Subjects.</hi> For pretended Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtent with Rebellion, but <hi>True Chriſtianity will be always attended
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:192125:21"/> with Loyalty.</hi> This will clear the Profeſſion of Religion from the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſion of ungovernableneſs; and ſet Us forward to that Kingdom, where He by whom Kings Reign, ſhall rule over all, and be all in all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joanna Browne</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> at the <hi>Weſt-End</hi> of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <head>A Sermon Preached by <hi>Benjamin Calamy</hi> D. D. on the <hi>9th Septemb.</hi> 1683.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Eccleſiaſtes 10. Verſe 20.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>Curſe not the King; no, not in thy thought,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>OF all Rebels they are certainly the worſt, that are ſuch out of conſcience; and no ſuch deſperate Villains as thoſe, who think to pleaſe God by Murders and Maſſacres. Other wicked men may be often checked, are ſometimes reſtrain'd by their conſciences, and dread of a future Judgment; but what evils ſhall they ever boggle at, who commit ſuch groſs wickedneſs out of complyance with their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? out of obedience to God? and expect to be rewarded for it in another world! And is it poſſible (by any thing We can do) to bring greater diſhonour to our Religion, or more effectually to prejudice Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Governors againſt it, than by making it to patronize and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance Faction and Rebellion? If this were the true genious of Religion, To make men Unpeaceable, Turbulent, Mutinous, Seditious, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It would then become the great intereſt of Princes to guard themſelves againſt It, as the very Peſt of Humane Society, and dangerous to the Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But thanks be to God, <hi>This</hi> is not the temper of <hi>Our Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity:</hi> Our Saviour's Religion begets in men the moſt gentle and meek,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:192125:22"/> patient and Governable Spirits, and is ſo far from being inconſiſtent with Loyalty to our Prince, that it is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> greateſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye and Obligation to it in the World, And there is no one can through off his Allegiance to his Earthly Soveraign, but at the ſame time He Renounces all duty and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards God.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine and diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England</hi> We all know what it is; It is ſtated and defin'd, and we are ſure that it condemns all diſloyal Seditious practices, <hi>on any pretence whatever. We</hi> muſt not compaſs, imagine deſire <hi>or contrive (Or invite)</hi> any thing that tends to the damage and prejudice either of our Soveraign Lord the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or of any that are Commiſſion'd or Authoriz'd by him, Soveraign Kings and Princes are God's <hi>Deputies</hi> and <hi>Vicegerents,</hi> ſet up by himſelf, and They derive their <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> from him alone. God Almighty the maker of us all is the only abſolute Lord and uncontroulable <hi>Sover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aign</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> part of his own <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> which he hath over his Creatures, he hath <hi>Delegated</hi> and <hi>Committed</hi> to Kings, who are the moſt Principal inſtruments and Miniſters of his providence in the World: Hence are they call'd Gods, and <hi>Children</hi> of the moſt High: <hi>Pſal:</hi> 82 6. God hath inveſted them with ſome part of his own Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, ſtamped his own Character upon them, and appointed Them in His place to perform and adminiſter even ſome part of his Divine Office (if I may ſo ſpeak) amongſt men; Thus conſtituting Them Earhly Gods, as to their perſons, ſacred; and as to their Actions, Accountable to None, but that Supereminent Divine Authority that gave them Commiſſion. This is not any new coyned Divinity, invented in favour of <hi>Arbitra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but is expreſly delivered in holy Scriptures, was profeſſed own'd and taught by the primitive Chriſtians and hath been the conſtant Doctrine of the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> Nay it is agreeable to the general ſence of mankind, and might be made out by Rational Evidence, if we had no other confirmation of it.</p>
            <p>That Supreme Governours have their Power and Authority from God alone, is expreſly delivered in Scripture; and that not only of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (who were evidently eſtabliſhed by God's appointment) but in general we are told <hi>Prov:</hi> 8. 15. 16. By me Kings reign and Princes decree Juſtice: By me Princes Rule, and Nobles, even all the Judges o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Earth. Thus <hi>Cyrus</hi> an <hi>Heathen</hi> Emperour is call'd God's Annointed <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45. 1. Thus ſaith the Lord to his Annointed to <hi>Cyrus;</hi> and in the laſt verſe of the preceding Chapter, he is call'd God's <hi>Shepheard (Prin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> being often, by reaſon of the Reſemblance betwixt the <hi>Paſtoral Offic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:192125:22"/> and Government, call'd <hi>Shepheard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>)</hi> I have made the Earth ſaith God by the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 27, 5, 6. and given it to whome it ſeemed meet unto me, And now have I given all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> theſe lands into the hands of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> my ſervant: Thus <hi>Daniel</hi> declareth that the Moſt High Ruleth in the Kingdoms of men, and giveth it to whomſoever he will. And he tells <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> Chap. 2, 37. that it was the God of <hi>Heaven,</hi> that had given him a Kingdom, <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Glory.</hi> In the new <hi>Teſtament</hi> nothing can be plainer, than the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the 13, <hi>Rom:</hi> where St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us that there is no Power but of God, that the Powers that be are ordain'd of God; whence in the next verſe he ſtyleth Magiſtracy or Government, the Ordinance of God; and in the <hi>4th</hi> verſe the Ruler is Called the Miniſter of God, To execute his vengeance upon Them that do Evil. It is plain that this was always the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as appears from the Booke of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies,</hi> wherein we are taught<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That the High Powers are ſet in Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by God; that they are God's Lieutenants; God's Preſidents; God's Officers; God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Commiſſioners; God's Judges Ordain'd of God himſelf, Nay, it hath been directly aſſerted in our Church, that the moſt High and Sacred Order of Kings, is of Divine right, being the Ordinance of God himſelf, founded in the prime law of nature, and clearly eſtabliſh'd by expreſs Texts both of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi> Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Nor indeed can it be well Conceiv'd or Reaſonably imagin'd from whence Kings and Soveraign Princes ſhould have right to Govern and Command, but from God alone, ſince He is the undoubted Lord of the whole Earth, and alone hath full Power and Right to Govern it: I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee, but that whoever ſhall goe about to Confer any Power of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or take upon himſelf, any ſuch Authority, over others, were it not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y God's Appointment and inſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ution, he would thereby put himſelf, upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſpoſing of Gods Right, without his leave, or ordering: ſo that Government or Supriority of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, or more, over others, is all Tyrany and Uſurpation upon God's Right, or els it muſt be granted, to be Ordain'd by God himſelf. And whatever the form of Government may be, or whatever hand the People may have in Chooſing or Deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the perſon, or perſons, that ſhall be inveſted with this Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, yet the Power and Authority it ſelf, is deriv'd only from God, and is neither Received of the People in Truſt, nor is the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Soveraign Power, anſwerable to them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the Adminiſtration of it: which is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times illuſtrated thus, Tho' the Wife may chooſe what perſon ſhe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, to make her Husband, Yet his Authority over the Wife; is not ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:192125:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:192125:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:192125:24"/> to her, nor doth ſhe confer it upon him, but it is of Divine Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſiſteth the Power, Reſiſteth the Ordinance of God ſaith St. <hi>Paul: To oppoſe and ſhake off his Majeſties Government, To Plot and Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> againſt him is to Rebell againſt God;</hi> And when <hi>We</hi> wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d not ſuffer our Lawfull Soveraign, whom the Divine Majeſty had appointed to Rule over <hi>Us,</hi> we did, by juſt conſequence, and fair in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, endeavour what we could to <hi>Dethrone God himſelf</hi> and proved Traytors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot only againſt our Natural Lord and King, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Heavenly Monarch himſelf, by whoſe Commiſſion he Reigns.</p>
            <p>That Wicked King <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kiah,</hi> of whom it is expreſly ſaid, 2 <hi>Kings,</hi> 24. 19. that he did that which was Evil in the ſight of the Lord; yet he is ſtile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the Prophet <hi>Jeremy, Sam.</hi> 4, 20. <hi>The Breath of our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils</hi> The fates of whole Kingdoms depend upon them. All that live under their Government are intereſted in them, and partake with them: And a <hi>Uillanous Invitation or Treache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous Attempt</hi> Succeeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Soveraign, may (I am afraid moſt juſtly, will) ſtab a whole Nation to the Heart, and fill all Places with <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Confuſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it not God's wonderfull Providence, that hath hitherto preſerved His moſt Sacred Majeſty. And did not the ſame Providence preſerve his Royal Brother, and himſelf, from the Fury and Rage of thoſe, who Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brued their Salvage hands, in the Sacred Blood of their Majeſties Royal Father? Hath not the ſame good Providence continually encompaſsed <hi>Them</hi> as with a ſheild, when their own Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts, then, and now again, in Arms<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſought both their Deaths and deſtructions? was it not the ſame Providence, that for a long time hid and Conceal'd <hi>Them,</hi> from the moſt diligent Search of Blood-thirſty Rebells, and at laſt after a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous manner provided an eſcape for them, and through Innumerable dangers, conveyed them ſafe to a ſtrange Land? was it not the ſame God who deferded and ſupported them then and ſtill continues ſo to do, in the unparallel'd caſe of his preſent Majeſty, againſt the moſt unnatural and blackeſt Treacherys, and Treaſons, that ever yet ſaw light, till at length by His own Right hand and Ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtretched Arm. He brought them ſafe again to <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Gloriouſly Reſtored</hi> the King, to his three <hi>Kingdoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho' it were realy ſo that <hi>We</hi> were oppreſſed, or treated harſhly, by Governors, yet <hi>We</hi> are not to give vent to our paſſion, in undecent Rayling, or Inveighing, againſt them, call'd in Scripture, Blaſpheming, or ſpeaking Evil of Dignities. Is it fit ſaith <hi>Elihu</hi> to <hi>Iob,</hi> to ſay to a King, thou art wicked; and to Princes; ye are ungodly.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:192125:24"/>
            <p>It cannot but be obſerved, almoſt by every man, that many of <hi>the Heads of this late Conſpiracy,</hi> were perſons Infamous throughout the whole Nation, for their Immortallities and Debaucheries; Notorious <hi>Whoremaſters! Adulterers! Drunkards! Murderers! Swearers!</hi> and what not? Now what a Fulſome thing is it, and to be abhor'd of all Honeſt men, to hear ſuch perſons as theſe ſet up for the great Patriots of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and the aſſertors of the Peoples Rights, and Conſervators of their Liberties and Religion? Are men of ſuch <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> Principles, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute Conſciences, fit to be truſted, either with Religion or our Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? or can we deſire any gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ater Argument, that they are mov'd by ſome other deſign; which they make under ſuch plauſable pretences.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>Us</hi> all be warn'd, to have a care of Reading Factious Books, and of imbibing antimonarchical principles, but more eſpecially that curſed <hi>Antichriſtian Principle,</hi> which hath done an infinite deal of miſchief a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>Us,</hi> and perhaps hath brought more into <hi>This Plot</hi> than any one thing els, I mean, That it is Lawful <hi>in ſome Caſes</hi> by Force and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce, to Reſiſt the Supreme Authority <hi>Eſpecially in defence of the True Religion;</hi> Particularly, if the King or thoſe commiſſioned by him, uſe Illegal Force to bring in another Religion, or to perſecute the Profeſſor of the true Keligion. Let us have a care of the Books, wherein ſuch Poyſonous Doctrines are taught, or of the Company of thoſe who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to believe them, leaſt before we are aware, they inſinuate themſelves into us, and ſo betray us to infinite miſchiefs</p>
            <p>Men do not become Traytors, and Reb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lls, in an inſtant, But firſt They begin with Murmuring and Complaining, then unmannerly talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Superiors, at length plain accuſing their proceedings, till by ſuch undutifull practices, they become conſcious to themſelves, that <hi>They</hi> have offended the Government, at ſo great a rate, as that they cannot be ſafe under it, and then in their own defence, they think of deſtroying it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kittilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church yard.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:192125:25"/>
            <head>Core Redivivus. A SERMON Preach'd by <hi>William Bolton,</hi> one of the Scholmaſters of the <hi>Charter-Houſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Numb. 16. 26.</bibl>
               <q>And he ſpake unto the Congregation, ſaying, Depart I pray you from the Tents of Theſe wicked Men, and touch nothing of Theirs, leaſt you be conſumed in all Their Sins.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>TO oppoſe <hi>Our lawful Magiſtrate,</hi> is againſt the ſenſe and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Chriſt's Church in all ages, even under the ſevereſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, I ſay in all ages, even under the ſevereſt Perſecutiors of Heathen Emperors, nay, under <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate. And if <hi>We</hi> ſhall reflect upon the Judicial proceedings of God Almighty in this kind, we ſhall find him ſo jealous of his own, as not to ſuffer in <hi>his Deputys</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and therefore by ſome ſecret and irreſiſtible power, He hath ſtill countermanded the deepeſt projects of Traytors. He hath ſplit their Councels, and ſtruck their moſt refined Policies, with fruſtration, <hi>Or a Curſe.</hi> You have heard how <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> (who had ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted, from their loyalty, no leſs than 250 Princes, men of renown, upon whom the Holy Ghoſt in the Text, faſtens no other character, than that of <hi>Wicked)</hi> ſuffer'd, both in themſelves, and accomplices, for their mutiny againſt <hi>Moſes.</hi> And let <hi>Abſolom</hi> ſteal the hearts of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from <hi>David, both his King and Father,</hi> Let ten of the twelve Tribes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim him King in <hi>Hebron;</hi> Let the <hi>Diſtreſſed David</hi> fly from his Royal
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:192125:25"/> Seat, and let his ungrateful and rebellious Son, poſſeſs <hi>Jeruſalem [London.]</hi> Let <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ophel</hi> adviſe <hi>Abſolo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o purſue <hi>David,</hi> his counſel ſhall be turn'd into folly, inſomuch that he ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> lay violent hands upon himſelf; and though the <hi>too indulgent Father</hi> gives command to ſpare his life, yet rather than <hi>Abſolom</hi> ſhall proſper in his Treaſon, his own beloved hair ſhall ſerve for an halter to execute him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> from <hi>chap.</hi> 15. to the <hi>19th.</hi> Let <hi>Sheba</hi> the Son of <hi>Bichri</hi> make a Party in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> againſt <hi>David,</hi> let him ſecure himſelf, in the ſtrong City, a Woman ſhall perſwade his own Followers to cut off his head, and preſent it unto <hi>David</hi>'s General; <hi>chap.</hi> 20 If you look into 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 11. you will find the reward of <hi>Athaliah</hi>'s Treaſon; She ſeizeth upon the Crown of <hi>Judah,</hi> and to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cure herſelf in it, ſhe (as ſhe imagin'd) ſlew all the Seed Royal: After ſix years en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of the Throne (without doubt ſhe ſuppoſed herſelf ſafe enough) when behold the King's Son (hid in the houſe of the Lord for ſix years ſpace) is brought forth by the loyal <hi>Jehojada,</hi> the High Prieſt, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed King, and the Traytoreſs <hi>Athaliah</hi> is juſtly ſlain.</p>
            <p>And in our Engliſh Annals we may find Examples enough of this kind: Let <hi>John</hi> uſurp the Throne due to <hi>Arthur,</hi> his elder Brother's Son, he taught but his Subjects to rebel againſt him; and after he had numbred as many troubles, as days of his Reign, he is thought to end his life by poyſon. <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, tho otherwiſe a brave Prince, yet <hi>becauſe he Diſpoſſeſſed his Father</hi> of the Crown, ſhall rue it in his Grandſon, his immediate Succeſſor, whom <hi>H.</hi> 4 <hi>(another Uſurper)</hi> bereaves firſt of his Throne, and a little after of his life too; But Divine v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngeance meets with him likewiſe, in his Poſterity; for <hi>H.</hi> 6. his Grandſon (tho as innocent and harmleſs a Prince as ever before him that enjoyed the Imperial Crown of <hi>England)</hi> hath his own Son ſtabb'd before his face, and himſelf ſome time after butcher'd by the ſame hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Let <hi>Rich.</hi> 3. murder his innocent Nephews in the Tower, let him poyſon his own Wife, that ſo he might marry his Neece; the only Heireſs to the Throne; yet God blaſts his deſigns, and bleſſeth this Nation both with his death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the happy Union of the <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Families, in the perſons of <hi>Eliz</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, <hi>Which Conteſt</hi> had coſt more Blood than twice Conquer'd <hi>France;</hi> Which, One would think, ſhould make <hi>all true Engliſhmen</hi> pray for the Succeſſion of the Crown, in a true lineal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent.</p>
            <p>From theſe, let us come ſome what nearer, and behold <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>6th</hi> upon his death bed, whom <hi>Northumberland</hi> works, and impoſeth <hi>to</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Lady <hi>Jane Gray</hi> his Succeſſor: <hi>The ſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity of the Proteſtant
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:192125:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:192125:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:192125:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:192125:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:192125:28"/> Religion was then, as now pretended,</hi> To which They knew <hi>Mary</hi> was averſe, And ſo ſoon as the King was Dead, the Lady <hi>Gray</hi> (againſt her own will is proclaimed Queen, in <hi>London;</hi> and her Ambitious Father in Law, <hi>Northumberland</hi> thinks all ſafe, as having nothing to oppoſe him but a Naked and defenceleſs <hi>(Tho a true)</hi> Title; when no ſooner <hi>Mary</hi> (tho' a Papiſt) aſſerts her Right to the Crown, but her Subjects <hi>(tho' they were Proteſtants)</hi> as one man riſe up in Arms to Defend [not to oppoſe or invade] the Succeſſion: <hi>They knew how many thouſand lives the diſpute about the Crown had coſt but a little before;</hi> Neither could they finde any motive then, no more than We can now in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> That gave any Encouragement againſt the Lawfull <hi>Heire.</hi> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution they might dread, but they would commit that Cauſe to God; and they had rather undergo the flames of Martyrdom, than be ſtigmatiz'd with the brand of Rebellion. Upon this the Conſpirators were defeated (and that without a Battle) taken and Executed. I might tell you of <hi>Wyat</hi>'s Conſpiracy in the ſame Queens time, and of many others in Her Siſters Reign.</p>
            <p>And as we often ſee Treaſon Severely puniſhed in this World, ſo it is much more dangerous to the Actors thereof in the World to come; I am ſure St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells <hi>Us</hi> ſo, <hi>Rom:</hi> 13. 2. They that Reſiſt, ſhall Receive to Themſelves Damnation, a very ſmall Encouragement (God knows) for <hi>Conſpirator and Uſurpers, to riſe up againſt and Dethrone a Lawfull King;</hi> Fortho' we ſhould grant (which ſeldom happens) that many Traytors might ſo far proſper here, as to ſecure themſelves from the hands of Juſtice; yet there is a King of Kings, from whom no power can ſhelter Conſpirators or ſuch (whether they be Lords <hi>Spiritual</hi> or <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral)</hi> that ſhall any ways <hi>Invite,</hi> or encourage an Invader, againſt their Lawfull Soveraign; And this Damnation, in the cloſe of all, will prove a ſad Prize of the moſt Fortunate, or Succesfull Treaſon whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>And in the 49 verſe of this Chapter, we may find no leſs than 14700 deſtroy'd, becauſe they maliciouſly cryed our againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> that they had killed the People of the Lord; And what People were they? why even the Bleſſed Conſpirators! <hi>Corah</hi> and his Accomplices! Good God! that any ſhould be ſo bold, or Fooliſh to call thoſe, whom the Holy Ghoſt in my Text, brands with the character of wicked Men <hi>The People of the Lord;</hi> No! No! <hi>They</hi> never were nor can be the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord, who Reſiſt Lawfull Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Norris</hi> at the <hi>Kings-Arms</hi> without <hi>Temple Bar</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:192125:28"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at <hi>Petworth</hi> in <hi>Suſſex</hi> by <hi>John Price,</hi> D. D.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 <hi>Corinth:</hi> 10, 10.</bibl>
               <q>Neither Murmer Ye, as ſome of them alſo Murmured, and were deſtroyed of the Deſtroyer.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>NEither the ſenſe of a natural allegiance, nor the Sacred Tyes of Oaths, nor Preferments, nor Honours, nor Riches could keep <hi>Some</hi> men, in the dutifull ſtation of Subjects; St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have the <hi>Corinthians</hi> take warning from the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> whoſe Murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and diſcontents, are recorded in Scripture, and recorded there not only To ubraid their ingratitude, but as the Appoſtle ſpeaks <hi>verſe</hi> 11. Theſe things happened to them, for Examples, and they are written for <hi>Our</hi> admonition, upon whom the Ends of the World are come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> gives a Caveat, Say not thou what is the cauſe that the former dayes were better than Theſe? For thou doſt not enquire wiſely, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this matter; The Murmuring Queſtioniſts of his Age, had the like before them, and they have been ſince; and ever will be! ſo long as time is, men will complain of the times, and the little portion of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs that God gives <hi>Us</hi> in this life, is di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>urbed by our own Reſtleſs and Repining nature, any little petry accident, at preſent, doth more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb <hi>Us</hi> than a load that is paſt, and gon off our ſhoulders, <hi>Iſrael</hi> was under the Miraculous protection, and deliverance of Heaven, but wants ſome little convenience; and preſently, we read of a loud and clamarous Murmuring; would to God We had dyed in <hi>Egypt!</hi> The hard Bondage they had felt, was gon off now; and the want but of a meals meat, in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:192125:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:192125:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:192125:30"/> the Wilderne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, put them to Murmur againſt God and their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors.</p>
            <p>As if it were not enough that man was born to labour, as the ſparks fly upward, but we ad, ſparks to the fire, when we are Children and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the diſciplin of the Rod, we complain that we were not born ſooner, and paſt the Correction of our Maſter; and when we are Old, we think we ware never ſo happy as when we were Children; indeed we are <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Thoſe phanſies that pleas'd <hi>Us,</hi> we are ſoon weary of, and ſeek for new; ſomthing it is that would pleaſe <hi>Us</hi> better, but what it is we know not; <hi>Nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bus atque Quadrigis petimus bene Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To Repreſent unto you the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Murmurer; firſt he is an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick;</hi> St. <hi>Inde</hi> ſpeaking of falſe Teachers, ſays that they are Murmurers, Complainers <hi>&amp;c. Iquietoe Hereticorum Curioſitates</hi> ſays <hi>Tertulian:</hi> They are always Reſtleſs, and always Prying; Creep into Houſes, and then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to affections, till their Murmuring diſcontents at laſt, break out into open Factions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Murmurer is certainly the State ſinner, The little grudgings that begin in Princes Courts, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oon ſpread into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and they are like the Poets <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Malum,</hi> the further the ſame goes the greater it grows, The Murmuring diſcontents in the ſtate, at laſt break out into open Rebellion (as <hi>We</hi> now ſadly ſee The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſaid as for this <hi>Moſes, We</hi> wot not what is become of him, The next thing we hear of them is, They make a <hi>Motion Calf,</hi> that is ſet up a Religion and Government of their own, The Tongue is a little Member ſaith St. <hi>James,</hi> but tis a great evil: and the Murmuring Tongue ſets the ſtate ſtill on fire; and Hell Fire ſhall be the Portion of <hi>ſuch Tongues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly the Murmurer is ever an envious perſon, and ſo an evil mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of a Socie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y; Murmuring is a diſtemper call'd <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a complaining without cauſe, and the envious man always doth this, Tis a nature that mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a near appreach to the Devils, The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of <hi>Iob</hi> is an Eye-ſore.</p>
            <p>Fourthly he is the Malicious man; delights to do Miſchief where he lives; is a trouble to himſelf, and will be ſo to his Neighbour; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no wonder if puniſhment doth attend him, for he is ranked by <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> among the ſeaven abominable things, that God hates, <hi>Him</hi> that ſoweth diſcord among Brethren. In ſhort a Murmurer is he that is every thing, that is Miſchievous, Blaſpheams-<hi>God,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> his <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour;</hi> and he is a burthen to the Earth, and to himſelf, neither good nor
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:192125:30"/> bad wheather pleaſeth him, Complains in War, and yet is diſcontented in Peace; pines away in Scarcity, and yet repines at plenty; when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>Summer,</hi> he longs for <hi>Winter,</hi> and when 'tis <hi>Winter</hi> wiſheth again for <hi>Summer,</hi> neither Times nor Manners pleaſe him, and could he call for them at his pleaſure, yet he would Murmur ſtill, of which we have a full iuſtance in the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ill Men,</hi> who have private deſigns of their own to carry on will be always complaining of Publick affairs; and their Complaints may ſomtimes ſeem ſo plauſible, that they may gain Proſelytes to their Faction, <note n="*" place="margin">I doubt not but there were many ſuch in England.</note> 
               <hi>Some</hi> of whom may not Mean ſo ill, as they do.</p>
            <p>Froward Men diſturb God's method of Mercy, and make it ever Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry in the Womb. God intended quietly and ſafely to lead <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt</hi> into <hi>Canaan;</hi> and the March of ſo many years might have been accompliſhed in ſo many days; but <hi>They ſtood in their own light</hi> and ſtopp'd the way againſt themſelves: They tempted God very oft, and ſo oft, that a patient and long ſuffering God, at laſt, ſware in his wrath that <hi>They</hi> ſhould not enter into his Reſt. This Sin of Murmuring is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an ill habit of the ſtomach, that corrupts the beſt meat; <hi>We</hi> Murmur at Mercys, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did at <hi>Manna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> tells us, that Habitual Sins have a guilt diſtinct from thoſe Sins of which they are Habits, and that they are more dangerous, becauſe the Sinner is farther off from Repentance: The guilt that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from thoſe Habits doth make a <hi>Callus,</hi> and fear the Conſcience, that the ſinner little thinks on it, That he is going down into the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of death, and he is enſnared into damnation, drown'd in perdition before he ſays <hi>Domine miſerere,</hi> or asks what he has done? The Habit of Murmuring is ſo univerſal. Hand joyn'd to Hand, Tongue to Tongue, that the ſence of the Guilt is loſt; and becauſe 'tis ſo 'tis a diſtinct guilt: for the greateſt Sinners have repented, as <hi>Murderers, Adulterers,</hi> yea and <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters</hi> too, who are in a peculiar manner <hi>Guilty Loeſoe Majeſtatis Divinae,</hi> and Traytors to the God of Heaven. The repentance of all habitual ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners is difficult, but the repentance of an Habitual Murmurer, is beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t with more than ordinary difficulties; for the Arguments that ſhould reach the guilt, are not well reducible to any ſingle Commandment and doth ſcarce affect the letter of any; And yet tis a ſin of a complicated guilt, affects both Tables, and moſt of the Commandments of Both. Beſides the Murmurer is not ſo ſoon as other Sinners convinced of his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:192125:31"/> Guilt, becauſe he hath fram'd a rule of rectitude to himſelf, and his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ens and ſhuts by that Rule, and ſo he ſtrains at gnats and ſwol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows Camels: Nothing ſo much troubled the Coſcience of a <hi>Neopolitan</hi> Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pherd, when he came to Confeſſion at <hi>Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter,</hi> as that he had taſted a little Cream the Lent before; but he had often Robb'd and Murder'd Paſſengers on the Mountains, and that troubled not his Conſcience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Father and Grandfather had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on ſo before: I believe all o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Us are ready to paſs a true and juſt ſentence here, but Reflect, here are ſome, who cannot digeſt aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t Form of Prayers; are offended at a <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice,</hi> ſtartle at the Croſs in Baptiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet can whiſper againſt the King, and whiſper to be heard too! talk loudly againſt <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieſts,</hi> cenſure all men; complain of every thing and be ſatisfied with nothing.</p>
            <p>Remember that God paſſed by ſome of the diſcontents of <hi>Iſr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el,</hi> but when <hi>They</hi> grew Clamorous and more <hi>Combined,</hi> his wrath fell in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſt them. And Remember that God hath other Eyes to ſee Sin, with than <hi>We</hi> have, and hath other Scales to weigh it in, than <hi>We</hi> have <hi>We</hi> our ſelves do not take ill Language kindly from our Neighbour, and can we think that God will from <hi>Us,</hi> when by our diſcontents We dayly Revile his Providence?</p>
            <p>When froward men do take a Liberty to ſpeak, write and Print what they pleaſe, and all with deſigns againſt the Government they live under, 'tis plain, They would be Governors themſelves, And when <hi>They</hi> have whet their Tongues, and ſharpn'd their Pens, <hi>They</hi> are not far off from drawing their Swords. And ſurely, without offence, I may now ask if this be not the preſent caſe of <hi>England</hi> againſt their natural Liege Lord and King?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Fiſh</hi> near the <hi>Fountain Taver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> in the <hi>Strand.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:192125:31"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the King at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> by <hi>Fra. Turner D. D.</hi> then Dean of <hi>Windſor,</hi> but ſince Biſhop of <hi>Ely.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſal. 144. 9. 10.</bibl>
               <q>I will ſing a new Song unto thee, O God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thou haſt given Victory unto Kings; and haſt delivered <hi>David</hi> thy Servant from the peril of the Sword.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THere is no queſtion but <hi>David</hi> in my Text had an eye to all the terrible hazards he had run before he was Crown'd, when <hi>Saul</hi> and his bloody houſe were hunting him like <hi>a Partridge upon the mountains:</hi> So that not his <hi>Own</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Not our King's Palace.</note> 
               <hi>Houſe</hi> which ſhould be a man's Caſtle, and his San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, not his <hi>Own</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">His Majeſty di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſturb'd at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night.</note> 
               <hi>Bed,</hi> which was made to be quiet in; not thoſe very places whither He fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d for Refuge, were free from the peril of the Sword.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o keep far enough off, not only from cold and frivolous parallels, but alſo from odious compariſons. I will only ſay, Do <hi>We</hi> not ſee a King preſerved from the ſame implacable enemy that has purſued him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove theſe forty years; but a much more formi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able enemy ſince he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd his enmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> than when he declared himſelf openly, even by ſetting a price upon the <hi>Moſt Sacred Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>David</hi> in his refl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctions upon the dangers or deliverances of his life, looks up to Heaven, he acknowledges, That <hi>the Race is not to the ſwift, nor the Battel to the ſtrong;</hi> and tho it be added by <hi>Solomon,</hi> that <hi>Time and chance happen to all things;</hi> his meaning was, that many things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ook indeed like Chance, tho guided by a hand of Providence, to moſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:192125:32"/> unſeen, which yet was moſt viſible to King <hi>David;</hi> in the whole courſe of his Fortunes; therefore he gives the Honour to God alone: He thanks him not only for his own proſperous ſucceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, but in behalf of <hi>All</hi> the Crown'd Heads in the world, <hi>It is he that giveth victory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto Kings:</hi> To the ſame great<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God of Heaven he aſcribes their <hi>Preſervation from ſo many Horrid Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iraties,</hi> as while there is a Devil in Hell, and ſo many of his Agents upon Earth [in <hi>England]</hi> will never ceaſe to be carried on; and when they are defeated or prevented, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the King of Kings that delivers his Servant <hi>David,</hi> or by parity of reaſon, any other Sovereign Prince, from the hurtful Sword.</p>
            <p>Now when <hi>David</hi> ſays, <hi>It is God that giveth victory unto Kings,</hi> it is to be underſtood virtually, and implicitly univer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al; he does not ſay that God always gives them victory: <hi>We</hi> know it has been given againſt the <hi>Beſt of Kings</hi> to the <hi>Worſt</hi> and moſt <hi>Ungrateful</hi> of all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: But the meaning is, that when ever th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe ſacred Princes are ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, as to be preſerved from the Sword, 'tis by an extraordinary vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilance of the Divine Providence over them, 'tis God is their Guardian, and not Man. And as [too late experience teacheth,] no King is to put his truſt in the number or the fortitude of his People, ſo neither is any People to confide in the wiſdom of their Heads, or in the vaſtneſs of their Body, to <hi>Oppoſe</hi> their Lawful Prince: For God in his <hi>Good Time,</hi> will make it appear that He governs the World, and He will make <hi>Them</hi> feel his hand that <hi>[Have Wreſted]</hi> or think to wreſt the Scepter from Himor Them that hold it for Him. <hi>Whoever They</hi> are that uſe indirect &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful means to raiſe or eſtabliſh, or but to <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cure Themſelves,</hi> They ſet up as it were for themſelves, without God in the World; They take the certain courſe either to miſcarry with their deſign; Or, if they do gain <hi>Their Point,</hi> yet their ſucceſs it ſelf is a J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dgment upon Them; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the greatneſs of their Sin, will be Their puniſhment; which, if It comes in this World, is commonly fetch'd out of the very bowels of the Sin that deſerv'd it, and ſo as the hand of God is <hi>illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly viſible</hi> in it. Such as will not truſt in God as a <hi>Deliverer from any Dangers They fear,</hi> but will take the Sword againſt <hi>Their</hi> Lawful Prince, <hi>upon any pretence whatſoever;</hi> Their Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence is read in the words of our Bleſſed Saviour; <hi>They that take the Sword ſhall periſh by the Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As an humble Confidence of God's Protection over us (if <hi>We</hi> reſolve to live in his moſt holy fear) is the moſt infallible courſe <hi>We</hi> can take to continue in ſafety; ſo, on the other ſide, all Policy that <hi>ſwerves from
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:192125:32"/> the ſtrict</hi> rule of Conſcience, does rather <hi>procure</hi> than <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ent</hi> extreme danger.</p>
            <p>The men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Gideon</hi> (that was in the time of the <hi>Judges) Rule Thou over us, both Thou and thy Son, and thy Son's Son alſo:</hi> By which they bind themſelves and their poſterity to be ſubject to him and his: But how did they keep their Faith with him? Much at the ſame rate as the unconſtant multitude are wont to keep it. As ſoon as <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deon</hi> is dead, <hi>Abimelech</hi> his Son by a <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bine,</hi> inſinuates himſelf into them; They fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſh him with Money under hand, wherewith he hires vain and light perſons to follow him; <hi>Multi quibus utile Bellum:</hi> And with Theſe he aſſaſſinates all the ſeventy legitimate Sons of his Father upon one ſtone; yet the People have ſtill that wicked partiality for him, as to make him their King; but how did this <note n="*" place="margin">And ſo is every Traytor; for the blood of all that is ſpilt in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, ſhall lye upon their heads.</note> Murdrous Traytor and his A betters proſper? <hi>Jotham</hi> the youngeſt Son of <hi>Gideon,</hi> and the only Son that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd the Maſſacre, cryes as a Prophet from God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Uſurper; and denounces that <hi>Fire ſhall come out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Bramble,</hi> (ſo in his parable he calls that Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Son) and that this Fire ſhall devour their <hi>Cedars of Libanon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Their Noblemen</hi> that raiſed <hi>[or invi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed]</hi> him. And we are told afterwards, that the <hi>men of Sichem dealt treacherouſly with Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech,</hi> as <hi>Thoſe</hi> that have been once <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llow Tray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ors</hi> to their lawful King, do ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om long continue faithful to one another. What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere follow'd? What Inſurrections? How the Fields were died with Gore, and how much Blood ran down the Streets of their City, you may read in that noble Story. And all the <hi>evil of the men of Sichem did God render upon Their own heads,</hi> and upon <hi>Them</hi> came the Curſe of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſtruſting of God, and (in ſtead of doing that which <hi>David</hi> preſſes ſo paſſionately, <hi>O tarty Thou the Lord's leiſure)</hi> being ready to ſay with that <hi>impious Nobleman, Why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arry We for the Lord any longer?</hi> Becauſe this fatal Impatience ſeems to be now one of our nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Sins, I ſhall urge againſt the ſad effects of it ſome ſuch examples as ſhall be national, and virtually a multitude of examples; <hi>Zedekiah</hi> the King of <hi>Judah</hi> having abſolutely ſubmitted to the great King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> '<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is ſaid he rebelled againſt King <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> who had made him ſwear by God: Therefore by the way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing a lawful Prince to whom an Oath of Obedience ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h once been take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> tho he be an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Prince, as <hi>Nebuchad ezxar</hi> was, <hi>is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> better</hi> than a down-right
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:192125:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:192125:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:192125:34"/> 
               <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ury, A wicked Rebellion:</hi> So <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the poor deſpiſed Prophet of God implies it to be throughout his Prophecy. But what if theſe were Perjur'd Rebels? yet this was always their note concerning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <hi>The Temple of the Lord! The Temple of the Lord</hi> are theſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> They were the Godly, they were the Saints; juſt as the True Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant! The true Proteſtant! is now the common Cry of <hi>Thoſe,</hi> who think that Title, a good Apology, &amp; a ſufficient Plea to legitimate Perjury and Rebellion; nay more, he is ſure to be call'd a Factor for <hi>Babylon</hi> (as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was) that dares but call it Perjury and Rebellion. But to return to my Story, what became of that Rebellion I was relating? That miſguided eaſy Prince was utterly loſt, his very eyes were not left him, but only ſo long as to ſee his Sons put to the Sword, and the People were carried Captives into that ſame <hi>Babylon,</hi> that heatheniſh Countrey, which they ſo juſtly abhorred</p>
            <p>Again, the ſame tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bulent and reſtleſs People, being after many ages in ſome degree re-eſtabliſhed by the valour of the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> had made an intire and neceſſary ſurrender of themſelves to the <hi>Romans,</hi> as to their Lords and Maſters. For fear of giving umbrage to the <hi>Romans</hi> of any other pretender to the Crown but <hi>Ceſar,</hi> their curſed Polititian <hi>Caiaphas</hi> was for putting our Bleſſed Lord to death: Theſe two words <hi>Venient Romani!</hi> the <hi>Romans</hi> will come, and take away both our place and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, were effectual Incentives to ſtir up the People to cry, <hi>Crucify him, Crucify him:</hi> As now to cry loud enough, Popery will come in and ſwallow <hi>Us up,</hi> ſerves all the turns of any great Incendiaries, to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k through all Humane and Divine Laws. What elſe could they intend (ſpeaking of the Phanatick Plot in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's time) but a Maſſacre? What other thing could they wiſh? What other cauſe of acting ſo deteſtable a Treaſon? For to take off a moſt merciful King, and his next Succeſſor; <hi>Who next to him hath ſhewed himſelf of a moſt reconcilable Temper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Complying men, ſuch as can ſit ſtill and be quiet under any Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, care not What In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ereſt prevails, and laugh at the notion of being State Martyrs: But I wiſh this ſort of men (who pleaſe themſelves w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h being ſo <hi>Paſſive</hi> in ſo <hi>Active</hi> times as theſe) would conſider what kind of cenſure, or ſentence rather, an Heatheniſh Legiſlator hath paſs'd upon them; Amongſt the Laws of <hi>Solon</hi> (ſays <hi>Plutarch,</hi> Writer of his Life) that is very peculiar and ſurprizing, which makes <hi>all Thoſe infamous, who ſtand Neuters in a Sedition:</hi> for it ſeems he would not have any One inſenſible and regardleſs of the Publick, and ſecuring his Private af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:192125:34"/> glory that he had not any feeling of the Diſtempers of his Country, but <hi>Preſently joyn with Thoſe that have the Right</hi> upon <hi>their ſide,</hi> aſſiſt and venture <hi>with Them</hi> rather than ſhift out of Harms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Theſe are the words of the wiſe man, ſtating and declaring the concern that every private man ought to ſhew, when his <hi>Prince</hi> (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Rebellion) or his Country (by Invaſion) is in danger. And <hi>David</hi> being yet a Subject, tells the people plainly, <hi>as the Lord liveth</hi> (ſays he) <hi>Ye</hi> are worthy to dye, <hi>Becauſe Ye have not kept your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Lord's Annoynted.</hi> Awake then <hi>You</hi> that together with the Land which the Lord gave, to your Forefathers, inherit their virtue too <hi>the old Engliſh Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Courage,</hi> Lay out your thoughts upon ſome thing more worthy of your ſelves, than are thoughts only of your own ſecurity: Let every one in his ſtation do his duty fearlesly: <hi>And they that doe ſoe,</hi> prove for the moſt part the wiſeſt aswell as the moſt Conſciencious, the ſafeſt aswell as the nobleſt and beſt Patriots: Let <hi>Us</hi> ſet it down to our ſelves that Honeſty is the true Policy, and let none make that curſed converſion of the propoſition, as if Policy were the true Honeſty; unleſs they mean to Revive that old abominable Gnoſtick principle <hi>of Compliance with any Uſurpations,</hi> or Impoſitions, for fear of ſufferings, for fear of that; which a Chriſtian would rather wiſh for his own ſake, could it be without other mens guilt, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Crown of Martyrdom. The Church (the Feild of God) has been manur'd and enriched with the nobleſt compoſt in the world, the blood of Martyrs; The times and Seaſons of the year are bounded out and Signalized by the dying days of Martyrs, The Chriſtian Temples are dedicated to the Memorials of the Martyrs; And <hi>Miracles were undeniably</hi> wrought at the Monuments of the bleſſed Martyrs. After all this, men of ſoft and ſmooth-Inſinuations would introduce a Principle of ſelf-preſervation (as they call it) as if it were unworthy, as if it were unlawfull to ſuffer any thing like Martyrdom, Nay as if it were more Chriſtian like, to be <hi>Rebels</hi> and Regicides, than to be ſo much as Confeſſors in the cauſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I hope now many of the Kings Enemies will change their note, and ſing Our new Song, But then let it come from the ground of the heart, And upon theſe terms They are welcome not only to Our Communion (to our Church, <hi>She never takes the Sword againſt her lawfull Sover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aign)</hi> but to that of the Angels in Heaven; for there is joy in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Angels of God over one Sinner that repenteth, then much more joy over many repenting Sinners. What a noble change, or rather
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:192125:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:192125:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:192125:36"/> what a Glorious transfiguration would be wrought upon <hi>Theſe men,</hi> that were lately Inſtruments of miſcief; would <hi>They</hi> now turn Saviours in their kind, ſuch as the Prophet gives God thanks for, <hi>Thou gaveſt them Saviours</hi> who <hi>ſaved them out of the hands of their Enemies, Nehem:</hi> 9. 27. I will not ſay the third part of the Stars are ſmitten down (as they were in St. <hi>Iohn</hi>'s viſion) yet now ſo many who ſhin'd heretofore in their proper Orbs <hi>are fallen.</hi> And yet the greateſt Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in the World may finde Room enough to exerciſe and ſhew it ſelf in a Thorough Penitent; as tis excellently argued by St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom,</hi> That <hi>David</hi> ſhew'd a more undaunted greatneſs of mind in daring to think of Surmounting the Sin, and the Shame, and to ſet up again for a Saint, after his Foul, Treacherous and Bloody offence in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> than he had ſhewn in his Single Combat with <hi>Goliah</hi> of <hi>Gath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Benjamin Took</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls Church-yard.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:192125:36"/>
            <head>The Religious Rebel. A SERMON Preach'd at <hi>South-Marſton,</hi> in <hi>Wilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> by <hi>Charles Powel,</hi> M. A.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10, 10.</bibl>
               <q>He falleth down and humbleth himſelf, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Poor may fall into the hands of his Captains.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>REbellion (ſays <hi>Samuel)</hi> is as the ſin of <hi>Witchcraft: Satan</hi> firſt Rebelled againſt the great Monarch of the World, and tho his Ambition tumbled him down from the bright Regions of Bliſs into eternall Chains of Darkneſs, yet his inſtruments carry on the ſame Rebellion ſtill; tho' the ſcene be changed, and the Plot carried on at a diſtance, the deſign is ſtill the ſame, only that <hi>Our earthly Rebels</hi> are in this the worſe Devils, that <hi>They</hi> dare Rebell againſt God and the King too.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Pſalm</hi> in general is a pathetical complaint of <hi>David</hi> to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God of the Pride, <hi>Treachery, Malice</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> of wicked men, who (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays) ſeek only Rebellion; and <hi>Theſe</hi> wicked men (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors tell us) are <hi>Thoſe</hi> whom he had maintain'd and preferr'd in his own Court, and were therefore the more wicked and the more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous; of which very perſons he ſays; It is not an open Enemy that hath don me this dishonour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diviſions are of late soe dangerous, that I ſhall not dare ſoe much as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:192125:37"/> to divide my Text, but will only raiſe from it this propoſition; That it is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> new thing for the worſt of men to make uſe of the ſacred name of Religion, to palliate the moſt abominable undertakings. <hi>Bloodſhed,</hi> the <hi>Murtherer</hi> of the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Defenders</hi> of Religion (Pious Kings and Princes) deſtruction and Maſſac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of their Fellow Subjects, pulling down and overturning of all polity in the World, muſt be all uſher'd in (as <hi>We</hi> ſee it this day) with the Lamb-like harmleſs voice of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: And tho' in theſe Glorious times of the Ghoſpel they cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly think ſo, yet <hi>They</hi> will pretend, that in all this <hi>They</hi> do God good Service; ſo true is that of our Saviour; <hi>They come to Us in Sheeps Cloathing,</hi> but inwardly <hi>They are Ravening Wolves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My propoſition has been ſo often and ſoe ſadly proved, even <hi>Among Our ſelves,</hi> that to go about to confirm it by Arguments or precedents were to light you with a Lanthorne, in the Sun-ſhine, or to perſwade you that you are wounded, when you are (now) Roaring under the ſmart and anguiſh of the Blow. <hi>An evil man (ſays Solomon) ſeeks</hi> only <hi>Rebellion. therefore a cruel Meſſenger ſhall be ſent</hi> againſt him. <hi>Prov:</hi> 17, 11.</p>
            <p>We muſt have a care how we hearken to Thoſe men, that make the greateſt noiſe about Religion, which is not a thing of Talk and Noiſe and Tumult, but a Quiet, Calm, Peaceable thing: The Author of it was the Lamb of God, who neither ſtirred up the <hi>Jews</hi> to Rebell againſt the <hi>Roman Heatken C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſar,</hi> nor did he ever make uſe of any Siniſter, or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent meanes to eſcape the hands of his bloody Perſecutors and Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiers, who envied him for nothing more than his Religion, which he came on purpoſe to plant among them, and which was to be water'd with his own Blood, and brought to perfection by his own Death. In all his Actions, in the whole courſe of his Life, he was a Pattern to them of Meekneſs, Gentleneſs, Peaceableneſs, and <hi>Sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ection.</hi> And truly I am affraid <hi>Thoſe</hi> men, who make ſuch an Hurry and Clutter about Religion, are not his Diſciples, nor did <hi>They</hi> ever learn it from the Prince of Peace, eſpeciall when They make <hi>Relligion the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Publick Commotions and Diſturbances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me now give you this Seaſonable Caution. Doth any one come to you in <hi>Samuel</hi>'s Mantle, in the Garb and Poſture of a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and in that Sacred Disguiſe falſy whiſper to you what that Aparition ſaid truly to <hi>Saul;</hi> That God is departed from the King, and become his Enemy (for <hi>ſuch Sprights</hi> alſo there are now abroad in the World, and <hi>Thoſe in Black too)</hi> Have a care now? and ſtand upon your Guard!
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:192125:37"/> Look Diligently about you! are you not got into Endore e're you are aware? Is not the Witch and the Devil at work now, inſtead of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> tempting <hi>You</hi> to ill thoughts of him, whom that more <hi>ſure word if Prophecy</hi> (the word of God) tells you, ye ſhall not dare ſo much as to think Irreverently of? Remember that Apparition was an Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary thing, never permitted but once, a thing that Frighted the Witch herſelf, and not like to be repeated again, for every Fantaſtick mans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake, that would pretend to Inſpiration. 'Tis true indeed; there are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch Spirits in the World, but they are <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Cademons or Wicked Spirits, Spirits of Rebellion and Miſchief and Murder, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> Prophecies of, 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3, 4. Trayterous, Heady, High-minded, Lovers of pleaſure more than Lovers of God, ſuch as St. <hi>Iude</hi> deſcribes, who Deſpiſe Dominion, ſpeak evil of Dignities; And theſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, have a form of Godlineſs; They appear like Lucifer himſelf, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is Tranſform'd into an Angel of Light, all Clad with the bright and Glorious Rays of pretended Sanctity, as if they were Sons of the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng, ſome of the <hi>Corps du Guard</hi> to the great King of Heaven: But then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave a care, <hi>Mulier formoſa ſuperne, De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>init in Piſcem.</hi> Beware of the <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en Foot</hi> under the Robes of light; for tho' they have the form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ineſs, yet you may be ſure they deny the Power of it, who endeavour to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſen and vilify thoſe perſons in your opinion, who bear the Image and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amp of Him, from whom they derive their Authority; <hi>By Me Kings Reign;</hi> And while they Command nothing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but what is in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſſion, are no leſs to be obey'd than he that ſent Them, and ſet them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er us, however They are not <hi>In any Caſe</hi> to be Reſiſted; for <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ever Reſiſt ſhall Receive to Themſelves Damnation. Rom:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3, 2.</p>
            <p>And when his Majeſty was Reſtored in meer Mercy to <hi>Us;</hi> for I can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>arce call it any to him, who ſeem'd to be brought back only to new afflictions, by the Ingratitude and Repeated Rebellions and Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es of a <hi>Stiff-necked and Hypocritical</hi> Generation, who have Repayd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll thoſe Bleſſings, that by Him were conveyed to <hi>Us,</hi> not only by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roachfull and Contumelious language, which <hi>Moſes</hi> calls Reviling of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Gods, <hi>Exod:</hi> 22, 28. But by atheiſtically, Sacrilegiouſly and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lliouſly Plotting and Contriving his death, to whoſe Mercy [now] <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to his Brothers God-like Act of Oblivion, ſo many among <hi>Us</hi> owe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe lives, which <hi>We</hi> are now Sacrificing to the God of Rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainſt him. A King ſo dear to Heaven, that it has ſhewn as many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acles in his preſervation, as Hell hath produced Plots even to a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:192125:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:192125:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:192125:39"/> for his deſtruction. I need not refreſh your Memories which the wonderfull Acts of Heaven in his whole life, which has had its black lines of affliction, more perhaps than any other King we read of, in the Murther of that glorious Saint; his Royal Father, the ſeveral Exiles of himſelf, and the Royal Family, and the preſent Calamnities, which now attend him, in all which he hath ſuffer'd and doth ſtill continue to ſuffer more than I can relate, or he could bear, were he not ſuſtain'd by the right hand of the moſt High while he not only was, but <hi>now is</hi> again what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays of himſelf, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Iournying often, in Perils of Waters, in Perils of Robbers, in Perils by his own Country-men, in Perils among Falſe Bretheren</hi> [Treacherous Favourites] <hi>in Wearineſs, in Painfulneſs</hi> &amp;c. And now let <hi>Us</hi> pray to God that he would move <hi>Us</hi> all to walk more uprightly, and more ſincerely before him, And that the ſame God would make <hi>Us</hi> for the future more Loyal to our King; that <hi>We</hi> may not <hi>any longer</hi> deal Hypocritically with the one, or <hi>Rebelliously</hi> with the other, That God may once more ſpeak Peace to his People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard:</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:192125:39"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preach'd in the Cathedral Church of <hi>Norwich,</hi> By <hi>William Smith,</hi> Prebend there.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſal. 107. 8.</bibl>
               <q>O that men would therefore praiſe the Lord for his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: And declare the wonders he doth for the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HAth the Nation ſcarcely wip'd Their Eyes dry for the Blood of the Incomparable Father, but muſt it be drown'd again in Tears, for the murther of his ſucceeding Sons? And that in a ſcene of cruelty more inhumane, and with a malice more infatiable than the former. [And may I now ſay (as this juncture ſtands) being from <hi>Men</hi> that were once the leaſt to be ſuſpected.] The rage of the Factions had then but the Blood of one King for its preſent gratification; but <hi>Our Zealo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> for the Cauſe could not glut their thirſt for Royal Blood, but by murthering (as it were) <hi>Two at one blow;</hi> the life of the <hi>Deareſt Brother</hi> too muſt be ſacrificed to their fury and deſign. So that (methinks) I hear the <hi>Saints</hi> of that complexion ſay of him, <hi>Here is the Heir, come, let Us kill him alſo, and ſeize on the Inheritance.</hi> [But let <hi>Us</hi> declare the wonders of God, for that the King hath eſcap'd the killing, tho the Rebels have aſſiſted an Uſurper to ſeize on his Majeſties Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.] A Prince who all along manageth the conduct of his own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Government, with ſuch a ſweetneſs and ingenuity of temper, that he never did, or can, chooſe to ſee his meaneſt ſubj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts ſo much as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neaſy, if <hi>Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inacy</hi> precludes not his Royal Kindneſs to relieve <hi>Them:</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:192125:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:192125:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:192125:41"/> In a word, a Prince that is every thing, that a character of any the moſt gracious King can repreſent him.</p>
            <p>And is it This? Such a King! that was deſign'd to be barbarouſly murther'd by his own Subjects! [and now as baſely betray'd by the moſt villanous treacheries!] O! are you not all ſtruck with ſuch an horrour at the thoughts of it, as even to forget <hi>You</hi> have a being at all? Don't all the Blood of <hi>Your Ueins</hi> chill to a ſtone, at the very notice of it? And are not your whole Souls, and all their faculties, ſwallow'd up with ſurprize and amazement? Why don't <hi>You</hi> cry to the Heavens and the Earth to be aſtoniſh'd, that it ſhould ever enter into the hearts of <hi>any</hi> of the Chriſtian name, to attempt ſuch acts, that would not only have juſtified the ſalvageries of the moſt brutiſh Barbarians, but even made Hell it ſelf comparatively innocent in its worſt conſults. Such acts! that do invert the order of the miſchievous Regions, and hath placed the Bottomleſs Pit (as it were) above ground, and hath ſo out-done Devils at their own art, that they ſhall for ever after be tormented with envy, as with a new kind of Hell; that there ſhould be among mankind (in a certain Iſland) greater Devils than Themſelves. Marvel not that I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in this rapturous manner, the Caſe requires it, and it is a defect not ſo to expreſs it. The Devil as General, with his Lieutenants in <hi>ſheeps clothing,</hi> under the <hi>Flag of a Thorough Reformation,</hi> had once again rallied the <hi>Whole Proteſtancy,</hi> that is, all the <hi>Hereſies</hi> that ever infeſted the Catholick Church in all ages, eſpecially the Reformados of the <hi>Knip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perdollian</hi> and <hi>Knoxian</hi> Regiments, to bear down before them all that's regular and loyal, learned and pious.</p>
            <p>And let us now behold further the ſad conſequences that have already, and are ſtill like to attend <hi>Us.</hi> Did you not ſee the enraged Vulgar turn their Plow-ſhares into Swords, and their Pruning-hooks into Spears, to execute what their bloody Leaders long fermented malice had before contriv'd? Every Village is now likely to become a ſeat of War, all united Neighbourhoods are now in danger of being turn'd into diſtinct Hoſtilities, and every ſingle perſon is like to be lyſted into one ſide or other to carry on the fatal, the ſad and diſmal work of a Thorough De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. How happy were <hi>We,</hi> when the armed Troops in our ſtreets march'd only as our Defence and Guard; When our Trumpets ſounded nothing but the welcome Joys of our common Safety; and our Drums beat <hi>Us</hi> every night to bed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for an unſuſpected quiet. [But alas, <hi>We</hi> muſt now awake amidſt all the diſmal Alarms of horrour and confuſion, and our beloved Countrey is like to be the Seat of that War, which
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:192125:41"/> is moſt juſt againſt Us: How could We dethron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted!]</p>
            <p>This Treaſon! this late Conſpiracy! was not only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>betted, but really managed and acted, by a conſiderable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>art of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ility, [Lords Spiritual and Temporal] who having aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by <hi>Petitioning, Proteſting and Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alling,</hi> gave the ſeditious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll aſſurance, that They own'd and headed their Cauſe. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Gentlemen, (or Wretches rather) that <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou</hi> ſhould co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be Tools, and to creep in the duſt, to humour a Pieviſh and unworthy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>action: That They ſhould go about to blend and extinguiſh that Light [the King] from whence They borrow'd their own Luſtre; and chooſe to fall from their own Starry Orbs, to turn <hi>Blinking Meteors</hi> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſty Regions, to ſhine only by the Favour of an unjudicious and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>nt multitude under the Reign of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Conſpiracy hath been greatly ſupported under the pretence, and by the obliging name of Religion. Now as Religion bears generally the moſt powerful Charm in the minds of men, and influenceth them to the higheſt reſolutions of acting, be the attempts never ſo difficult or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous: So muſt the danger of any evil procedure be encreaſed, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath gain'd ſuch a prevailing abatement. And ſuch was our Caſe. All the Factions (tho in other things they may irreconcilably diſagree, yet) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>curr in this one common principle, <hi>That they mans Religion is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s own Private Conſcience,</hi> which he is to believe is the immediate dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate of God, and which he is bound indiſputably to follow. Now when this notion of Religion is entertain'd, it ſets up in every factious mind an uncontroulable Tribunal, which governs with a power ſuperior to all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mane reaſon, laws and authority; and gains ſuch an aſcendant over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch mens thoughts and actions, that like the Commanders power in the Goſpel, <hi>I ſay to one Man, come, and he cometh; and to another, Go, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> goeth.</hi> Go; ſaith Conſcience, fetch me a Chain, to <hi>bind this King, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Thoſe iron Fetters, to tye down thoſe Nobles;</hi> It's diſpatch'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut diſpute: And if then it ſaith, <hi>Go and pluck down thoſe Idolatrus Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ures, and let thoſe ſuperſtitious Miniſters be caſt out of them;</hi> if ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ence be but tinctured from Scripture, that thoſe are Groves and High <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aces, and theſe are <hi>Baalitiſh Prieſts and Dumb Dogs,</hi> the work is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one in an inſtant. When this Soveraign Conſcience enjoyns <hi>this Oath</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be taken; another, to be ſuperſeded, or broken; ſuch a Jury to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ack'd, and ſuch a Verdict to be given, let an innocent mans life, or even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſafety of an whole Nation lye at ſtake, He can no more ſuſpend his
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:192125:42"/> Duty, than violate his Credit of being of the Godly Party. Nay if <hi>Blood</hi> lyes in the way of Reformation, 'tis but Whiſpering into Conſcience a Text or two, and it bids the man (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>it be againſt whom it will) Goe, and utterly deſtroy thoſe Sinners the <hi>Amalakites,</hi> and Fight againſt them till they be conſumed, as he finds it, 1 <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> 15. 18. Or if he Reads, Curſed be he that doth the work of the Lord negligently, and that keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Sword from Blood, as he is told <hi>Jer:</hi> 48. 10. Or if he but hears a Curſe ye <hi>Meroz,</hi> unleſs you raiſe a Regiment to fight the Lords Battels; The man of Conſcience can no more reſiſt ſuch a call, than if a Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from Heaven had ſet him at work. And what miſchief theſe and ſuch like deſtructive principles have done <hi>We</hi> all know, and are now like ſadly to ſmart under the miſerable conſequence of them. But when ſhall the Prophecy of the <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> be accompliſhed among <hi>Us,</hi> who told his Son (our Soveraign Lord) <hi>That when the mask of Religion ſhould be Pull'd off the Face of Rebellion;—He might then ſee happy Days.</hi> But inſtead of that, Doe <hi>We</hi> not now ſee three Kingdoms im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broyl'd in the moſt unnatural War, or which is worſe made Slaves to the moſt unnatural Tyrants! Tho' we have not yet heard the ſad Tydings of Cities lay, in Aſhes, or of, Fields covered with the Slain, yet <hi>We</hi> have juſt; alas too juſt! reaſon to fear that deſtruction attends <hi>Us</hi> at our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dores; And We have ſeen that the Innocent and Loyal have been eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where made a Prey, to Satiate the Malice of a Revengful Faction! And for their ſakes the Nation is <hi>Now</hi> again become the Reproach of Chriſtianity, and Scorn of Man-kind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:192125:42"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge</hi> by <hi>Miles Barnes,</hi> D. D.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>St. <hi>Luke</hi> 19. V. 14.</bibl>
               <q>But his Citizens hated Him, and ſent a Meſſage afoer Him; ſaying, <hi>We</hi> will not have this Man to Reign over <hi>Us.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe Jews were always a Moody Head-ſtrong People, Impatient of any kind of Government, <hi>Theocracy</hi> it ſelf could not pleaſe them, They Murmured againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> &amp;c. And when the <hi>Meſſias</hi> appears as <hi>Moſes</hi> had don before in this great Junct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure of hardſhip, They adhere to their Oppreſſors, and ſhamefully reject the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Saviour; by Libelling his Government in general, by throwing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon his perſon in particular, Is not this the <hi>Carpenters</hi> Son? by traducing his life and converſation, making him a Winebibber, a Friend of <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Sinners;</hi> by making baſe Reflections on his <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> and chief <hi>Miniſters;</hi> by undervaluing his Doctrine, as inconſiſtent which the Pomp and Grandeur of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, by making him an Innovator, a diſturber of the <hi>Eſtabliſh'd Religion;</hi> and laſtly (as the Height of their Malice) by Proclaiming him a Traytor and Enemy to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> as having Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſter ends to ſet up a Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th Monarchy, in oppoſition to the Fourth. And when all their pretences were Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed, and they Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to the laſt effort of Obſtinate Rebels, to own <hi>Rebellion for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions ſake,</hi> then They Magiſteriouſly reſolve themſelves into the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty of their own <hi>Wills,</hi> and conclude againſt all Government in a direct <hi>Nolumus Hun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> We will not have this man to Reign over <hi>Us,</hi> But can they think he will not Reign over them? Yes he does and will too at his laſt terrible Advent, when he ſhall come with all the Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:192125:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:192125:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:192125:44"/> of Majeſty to Judge the World, Pronounce Sentence upon <hi>Theſe Wicked Citti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ens,</hi> and make Them the Vaſſals of Eternal vengeance, <hi>The certain Doom of all unrepenting Rebels!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſorry to tell you, that the frequent Tumults and Inſurrections which have infeſted the Reigns of our Britiſh Kings, gave occaſion to that Sarcaſtical ſaying; <hi>Rex Angliae, Rex Diabolorum;</hi> but you may tell your ſelves, that <hi>Theſe</hi> Devils never Acted more like Devils<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> than ſince They were poſſeſſed and guided by the Turbulent Spirit of our Modern <hi>Phariſees</hi> the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> who are the very <hi>Cittizens,</hi> that from their firſt Inſtitution have ſhewn their hatred againſt Monarchs and Monarchy. <hi>John Calvin</hi> founded his Presbytery in Treaſon and Rebellion, the <hi>Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens</hi> having prepared his way by expelling from <hi>Geneva</hi> their <hi>Lawful Prince</hi> and Governor, <hi>Which violent Act was Encouraged, approved</hi> and confirmed by <hi>Calvin;</hi> and it has ever ſince been carried on by <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Sedition.</hi> Never was it Received into any Church, but it preſently diſſolv'd the Catholick unity of Faith, and broke the Bond of Peace; never into any State, which it did not embroil and throw into very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Convulſions; never into any Family, which it did not divide, and ſet at variance; never did it get poſſeſſion of any ſingle man, whom it did not ſtrangely transform with Pride and Moroſneſs, made him unfit for Civil Society and Common Converſation.</p>
            <p>Have the <hi>Presbyteria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> in any of their Synods cenſured or condemn'd the pernitious Tenets of <hi>Calvin</hi> or <hi>Beza?</hi> has <hi>Any</hi> of them had the grace to diſown or write againſt their Dethroning Doctrines? if they have their Books have proved very ineffectual, for if <hi>We</hi> paſs from their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to <hi>Their Practices,</hi> We ſhall find that They have always been of a Turbulent, Imperious and Bloody Spirit. And there have not been wanting <hi>Some Church Trimmers,</hi> ſtill retaining a Fellow-feeling for the Cauſe, who from the Pulpit have endeavour'd to clear them, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay the guilt of their Horrid Murthers chiefly upon the <hi>Popiſh Prieſts;</hi> though they cannot finde the name of one <hi>Papiſt</hi> in the whole Liſt of True Proteſtant Regicides.</p>
            <p>The Principle of <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>roning</hi> or Depoſing Kings (charged upon the <hi>Jeſui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s)</hi> has been publickly cenſur'd and condemn'd as impious and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous in ſeveral Forreign Unsverſities, written againſt by men of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communion, and is moſt ſolidly and unanſwerably confuted by <hi>Barclay</hi> in his excellent Book <hi>De poteſtate Pap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> &amp;c. which book is dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to <hi>Clement</hi> the <hi>Eighth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prerogative never ſuffer'd, no great Statesman has ever been
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:192125:44"/> diſgrac'd, nor the Church of <hi>England it ſelf</hi> (nay the Libertys of the People) ever <hi>Wounded,</hi> But a dreadful Outcry of <hi>Popery</hi> has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded, No man could ſhew his Fidelity to the Monarchy, but he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently blaſted with the odious Title of a Court or a Church <hi>Papiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Speaking againſt the Bill deſign'd to exclude his Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York</hi> (now King) ſays this Reverend Divine. To ſay nothing to the Rude form obſerv'd in the penning of this Bill, that 'twas drawn up by a perſon ſince accuſed of High Treaſon; And to paſs by the Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the Contrivers, againſt a Prince of ſuch Eminent virtues; who has ventured his Royal Blood as frankly for the good of his Country, as the meaneſt Subject in it, &amp; who was even then actually manifeſting his unalterable Loyalty and affection to his Soveraign in Reducing <hi>Scotland</hi> to their Obedience; and We have at this hower great reaſon to be thankful to him for his Wiſe and Proſperous Conduct in that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faire.</p>
            <p>And I do here publickly declare; what was always my judgment, that I doe believe no human Acts or Power in the World can <hi>de jure</hi> hinder the deſcent of the Crown upon the next Heire, which is his <hi>unalterable Right</hi> by Religion, Law, Hiſtory and Reaſon.</p>
            <p>And now if We conſider the quality of <hi>This Helliſh</hi> Conſpiracy, It is compounded of ſo many malignant Ingredients, that it looks more like a confederacy againſt Religion, Morality and the Common Sentiments of Humanity, than a Conſpiracy againſt the Frame, Conſtitution and Adminiſtration of the Government, Ambition, avarice and Revenge have often lead men and bewitch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d them into Treaſonable <hi>Aſſociations</hi> But <hi>This</hi> ſeems to be the ſole reſult of abſtracted malice, of men aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd to the curſe of a Reprobate minde; who after having Travell'd through all the ſlow methods of Sedition, have now at laſt taken Arms and begun a moſt Bloody Rebellion againſt the Lord's Annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>And now what ſtorms are coming upon Us! what Devaſtations and Spoyles (by Fire and Sword) may we juſtly dread. And the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alas! may now become a Theatre of War and Feild of <hi>Blood;</hi> And the ſtreets fill'd with the Cryes of Widdows, and the Fatherleſs, with <hi>Murders, Rapins, Inceſt, Adulterys, Sacriledges, Maſſacres.</hi> and <hi>Conflagrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> And what ſatisfaction now can any Loyal Subject have to think of Surviving the Ruines of the Government? or to live in a Land Polluted and Stain'd with <hi>Blood?</hi> to ſee daily before his Eyes the dismal ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of his enſlav'd undone Country? or to live in pepetual Fears of being
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:192125:45"/> made a Sacrifice himſelf? But it hath hitherto pleaſed that God, who allotteth to Atheiſts and Rebells a portion with the Hypocrite, to reſcue and preſerve his Majeſty from the Paws of theſe <hi>Bloody Miſcreants,</hi> Hence it appears, That good Kings are the immediate care of God; and that They ſhould be ſo, ſeems agreeable to the Oeconomy of his Providence, and is confirm'd by Examples in all Ages. For They are his Annoynted, His Vicegerents, ſet over Us by his appointment, and are therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled to a ſpecial Right in the Divine Providence. Of this Truth his preſent Majeſty, with the late King his Royal Brother have been very Eminent Examples through the whole courſe of their Reſpective Lives.</p>
            <p>And that which ſeems Truly deplorable in this Execrable Treaſon, is the Hardineſs and Impenitence that accompanies This Rebellion, and purſues the Rebells to the very moments of their Deaths. But wo! be to <hi>Thoſe</hi> wretched Guids, who lead Them into both; <hi>Thoſe</hi> Betrayers of Souls! who inſtead of diſpoſing men to Chriſtian Obedience, have cauſed Them firſt to Rebell, and then inſtead of diſpoſing Them to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance have encouraged them in the Rebellion; And then at their very Deaths have forc'd them (as it were) to Publiſh ſuch Iuſtifications as ſeem written with deſigne to incite their accomplices to carry on the work here, whilſt they are anſwering for it in the other world. and this conſideration is enough to make the hearts of all good Chriſtians Ake. And We muſt now pray, that as God hath hitherto preſerved the King, ſo that Juſtice may overtake thoſe Rebells and Traytors whom Mercy cannot Reclaim.</p>
            <p>In a word then, as <hi>We</hi> are thankful to God for the preſervation of his Majeſty hitherto, ſo let Us implore Protection over him for the time to come, That he may daily Receive freſh Acceſſions of Strength and Splendor, and be Recompenced for <hi>the times, wherein He hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered Adverſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O Lord ſave the King,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And bleſs thine Annoynted;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Send Him help from thy holy Hill,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And evermore mightily defend Him.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let the Enemy have no advantage over Him;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor the Wicked approach to hurt Him.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Amen.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Lonndon,</hi> Printed for <hi>R: Royſton</hi> his Majeſties <hi>Book-ſeller.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:192125:45"/>
            <head>A Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mon Preach'd before the Lord Mayor <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> By <hi>Henry Hesketh,</hi> Miniſter of St. <hi>Hellens.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2, 15.</bibl>
               <q>For ſo is the will of God, that with Well-doing you may put to Silence the Ignorance of Fooliſh-men.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WE then moſt truly honour God, when we expreſs a great ſenſe of his Power and Soveraignty over us, in our Lives: And we then only glorify and acceptably praiſe Him, when we live according to his Commandements acknowledg the reaſonableneſs and goodneſs of his Laws, and chearfully do thoſe things, that are pleaſing unto Him. Among theſe, there cannot well be an higher inſtance, than to live up to the <hi>Principles</hi> of that Excellent Religion, that he has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>To be the Meaſure of all our Actions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To enquire now what was <hi>The Cavil</hi> and objection which theſe <hi>Foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> men made againſt Chriſtian Religion, which the Apoſtle in the Text hath reſpect unto, and would have Silenced? And this may eaſily be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd, by conſidering the two verſes immediatly preceding the Text; In which the Apoſtle doth preſs the duty of <hi>Obedience</hi> and Subjection to <hi>Our</hi> Lawful Governors, both <hi>Supream</hi> and <hi>Subordinate; Submit Your ſelves</hi> to every Ordinance of Man, whether it to be the King as Supreme, or unto Governors, as thoſe that are ſent by Him. And this he preſſeth by an Argument that can never fail of effect upon a good man, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for the Lord, and out of Conſcience to him, whoſe Inſtitution Government is, and who hath commanded Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction to it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Upon which <hi>Theſe words</hi> immediatly follow; by which <hi>We</hi> plainly underſtand, that the Objection which he enjoyns this Subjection in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:192125:46"/> of, was that old and early Clamour, that Chriſtian Religion was an Enemy to Government, and the profeſſors of it Factious and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious perſons, The great Clamour againſt the Chriſtians, upon which that great uproar againſt them at <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> was ſtirred, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 6, 7. was this, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heſe that have Turned the World up-ſide down, are come hither alſo; and Theſe all do contrary to the decrees of</hi> Caeſar, <hi>ſaying there is another</hi> (one Jeſus) <hi>King.</hi> This you will alſo finde the chief thing in the accuſation againſt St. <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 24, 5. For we have found this Man a Peſtelent fellow, and a Mover of Sedition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I doe most readily confeſs, that were this accuſation true, were Chriſtian Religion <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> with Government, an Enemy to it, or a <hi>Diſturber of it,</hi> there could not be an objection that would be more fatal to it; all the Reproach and Dishonour that men could load it with, were juſt, there were no apology to be made for it, nor any thing to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, but that all the world ſhould combine together againſt it. All men that have any becoming thoughts of the Providence and Goodneſs of God, how tender he is of the good of Mankind, and how largly he hath provided for it, how wiſely he conducts the courſe of humane affairs, and ſteers them by Rules, which would make them, and all things elſe that is happy, can never beleive <hi>That to be a Divine Religion,</hi> or be perſwaded to accept it as coming from God, which perplexeth the courſe of things, and defeats theſe good purpoſes of God in the World. God is the God of Order and not of Confuſion, the Author as well as Lover of Concord and Peace, and not of Ruine and Diſſention among Men; And therefore can never be the Author of any Religion that is deſtructive of the One, and naturally effective of the other, among them. And it therefore greatly concerns all <hi>Thoſe</hi> that hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any Reſpect for the Chriſtian Religion, to be ſure to keep it clear from any Objections of this kind.</p>
            <p>The Ancient Apologiſts have taken care <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in their Noble defences of Chriſtian Religion, to clear it from this Scandalous Reflection, <hi>By ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing to the known Doctrines and Principles of it;</hi> They challenge the World to inſtance in any one ſaying in the new Teſtament, whether there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the leaſt hint or encouragement given to Rebellion, or any thing that can warrant the <hi>leaſt undutifull</hi> Carriage towards our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors? Or rather, whether there be not enough aſſerted there, to aſſure Government, and to engage all perſons to Subjection, upon better ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, and ſtronger Reaſons, than a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y yet were ever made uſe of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, For here the Reaſon of Subjection is layd deep, and charged im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:192125:46"/> upon the Conſciences of men, Reſiſtance is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing</hi> the Ordinance of God, and Damnation is expreſſly threat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. And yet I muſt needs ſay to the dishonour of Some men, That <hi>They</hi> have Robbed Chriſtian Religion of this way of Defending itſelf, and defeated the effect of this appology for it.</p>
            <p>Obedience is not only recommended, upon the great advantages of quietneſs and Peace, of happineſs and Order, that reſult to the World from it, nor backed with the Sanctions of Temporal Puniſhment to Thoſe that Rebell; but it is preſſed upon Reaſons of Conſcience and Duty to God, and the danger of incurring that Eternal Damnation that is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Hell, for the Lawleſs and Diſobedient.</p>
            <p>Kings will be better pleaſed, and ſatisfied with the quiet and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Lives of their Subjects; their chearful obedience to their Laws, and Their ready complyance with their pleaſure, than with all the formal Careſſes, and Protestations of Loyalty and Love. And I wiſh <hi>Some</hi> men of late had not given Them too great cauſe to conclude, that <hi>Mens Practices and Prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſions doe not always go together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The good Christians of Old were in all caſes peaceable and ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, <hi>They</hi> readily obeyed, and heartily pray'd for their Governors, Even when mos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Barbarouſly and unjustly provoked to the contrary; ſo that not <hi>one Chriſtian</hi> dyed as a Rebel or a Traytor, in all the Early Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions of Christianity, nor for ſeveral Centuries; And you may challenge any of our modern Factors for Treaſon to inſtance in One. Nay, it is well known that even <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate acquits Them from this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſion, and upbraids his Heathen Subjects, with the Obedience and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty of the <hi>Galileans</hi> (as he ſcornfully calls them) which is the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable teſtimony, for coming from the mouth of the Bittereſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that Chriſtiani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ever had.</p>
            <p>And now alas! amongſt all the ſad Circumſtances of <hi>Our</hi> late Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Rebellion, there are none <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> ought more to be concerned for, than the Impiety and Guilt of the Conſpirators, and the advantage that ſome men will take hence, to <hi>Reproach the Proteſtant Religion.</hi> Oh! Curſed Impi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty and Hypocricy! are theſe things becoming True <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants?</hi> Is this the effect of all your Starch'd and formal Godlineſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Doe all your Oaths and Vows of Loyalty, and ſervice to <hi>Your King?</hi> Do all <hi>Your</hi> appeals to God, for the ſincerity of your Intentions? Do all your Solmn Proteſtations of care and concern for his ſafty, come at laſt to this? good God! that Plots and Conſpiracys againſt the King, Nay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>n Rebellion it ſelf, ſhould ſhelter themſelves under the Goſpell! And Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:192125:47"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to Colour that, which almoſt above all things it abhors. What ſhall we ſay of ſuch men? who can help <hi>U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to Names and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters bad enough for <hi>Them?</hi> who have put off not only Religion, but Humanity, and are Actualy commenced Devils.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Bonnick</hi> at the <hi>Lyon</hi> near St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd by <hi>John Harriſon</hi> D. D.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 <hi>Sam:</hi> 18. 28.</bibl>
               <q>And <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> called, and ſaid unto the King, all is well. And he fell down to the Earth upon his Face before the King, and ſaid bleſſed be the Lord thy God, which hath Delivered up the Men that lift up their hand againſt my Lord the King.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe Rebellion that was to begin at <hi>Heb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on,</hi> did happen under the pretence of paying a vow unto the Lord, that is, under the Veil or Diſguiſe of Religion, <hi>Abſolom</hi> ſaid to the King, Let me go and pay my vow, which I have vowed unto the Lord in <hi>Hebron, 2 Sam:</hi> 15. 7. Nothing more uſual than to give out, For the cauſe of Chriſt! whilſt under that vizor, <hi>They</hi> Act parts quite contrary to his Holy Doctrine and Bleſſed Example. And this is ever obſervable, in a well formed Conſpiracy (if a Conſpiracy can in any ſence be ſo expreſſed) Firſt, To ſettle it ſelf <hi>Under ſome Chief Leader,</hi> that by Popular Arts
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:192125:47"/> hath inſinuated <hi>Himſelf</hi> into the Multitude, Giving <hi>Himſelf</hi> out to be ſome mighty one, And what he wants of a juſt Title (as that ought ever to be maintain'd in an Hereditary Kingdom) He will make good in his defence of the <hi>Peoples Religion,</hi> Eſtates, Lives and Fortunes.</p>
            <p>The late Lord <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> encouraged by this <hi>Scotch</hi> Doctrine. <hi>That it is Lawful to defend a mans Conſcience by open Force againſt any Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> whatſoever, did dare adventure his Body <hi>(Yea I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>remble)</hi> his very <hi>Soul</hi> on this falſe bottom, ſo his Execreable paper ſeems to import, But inſtead of a Faithful <hi>(I fear)</hi> he met with a Faithleſs Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor: <note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> For who (that is not reſolved to quit humanity) will believe that to be Religion, which is <hi>Maintain'd</hi> with <hi>Treaſons</hi> and <hi>Murders</hi> of the moſt Purple <hi>Dye?</hi> And here we may obſerve, of what Miſchievous Conſequence any Combination is, whether influenced by ſelf-Intereſt, <hi>Pride, Ambition, Spight</hi> or <hi>Malice.</hi> When <hi>We</hi> are once lead out of the Kings High-way of <hi>Honnour</hi> and <hi>Honeſty,</hi> into any By-paths of our own, <hi>We</hi> ſoon fall into the Broad road of Rebellion.</p>
            <p>Having taken a Survey of <hi>This Helliſh</hi> Conſpiracy, a ſuddain Horrour here Seifeth my trembling heart, at the ſad apprehenſions of what hath already, or may ſtill, moſt juſtly befall <hi>Us,</hi> The diſmal conſequences of a <hi>Bloody War! &amp;c.</hi> The face and voice of an <hi>Angel</hi> (which hitherto hath been for <hi>Religion, Eſtates, Lives</hi> and <hi>Liberties)</hi> is now like to be changed into the hands of a Devil, who may rend thoſe deareſt Intereſts into a thouſand pieces; And the bleeding marks of the Laſt Rebellions, being Scarſe out of our ſides, <hi>We</hi> are now again like to be turned into avery Shambles.</p>
            <p>But ſurely <hi>We</hi> that have been ſo many years, a Laſting mark of Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my (over the habitable Earth) for <hi>Murdering</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of Bleſſed Memory, and Betraying his preſent Majeſty, as <hi>Judas</hi> did his <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> can no longer delight, in a continuance of ſuch diſgrace, as wants a Parallel. Have <hi>We</hi> forgot our Oaths of <hi>Allegiance?</hi> Have <hi>We</hi> caſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind <hi>Us</hi> all paſt favours from the Crown? to Betray our Truſt, to lift up our hands againſt God's Annoynted! ſure there are <hi>Some,</hi> the better they be dealt with, the worſe ſtill ye ſhall find them, And of Theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly <hi>David</hi> was moſt in danger.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Crook</hi> at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:192125:48"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preached on the Thanksgiving day <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by <hi>Edward Pelling</hi> Chaplin to the Duke of <hi>Somerſett.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34, 19.</bibl>
               <q>Many are the Afflictions of the Righteous; But the Lord delivereth Him out of them all.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe ſpecial Providence of God is ſeen in nothing more, than in watching over Princes, in preſerving <hi>Them,</hi> and their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and in ſupporting their Government For the hearts of <hi>Men</hi> are naturally ſo impatient of Subjection, and ſo greedy of Power; their particular intereſts are ſo divided; their deſigns are ſo various; their Paſſions are ſo violent; their Principles are ſo different; their minds are ſo ſett upon <hi>Villany</hi> and <hi>Miſcheif,</hi> (and what through <hi>Ambition</hi> or <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetuouſneſs,</hi> or <hi>Diſcontent)</hi> their Spirits are ſo reſtleſs, that 'tis by a daily Miracle that Princes live, and 'twould be impoſſible for them to be ſafe one Moment, did not the immediate had of God <hi>(of whom alone They hold their Crowns)</hi> Shelter and Protect Their Perſons, and overule the Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Turbulent and Blood-thirſty People.</p>
            <p>Perhaps noe Prince living ever had ſuch ample experience of this, as King <hi>David</hi> had; unleſs <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> will except our own dread Soveraign, whoſe caſe comes neareſt to a Parallel: <hi>Davia</hi>'s Title to the Crown was <hi>Unqueſtionable:</hi> His Government was equal and eaſie; His heart was of a Tender and Compaſſionat Temper; He was ready to forget the greateſt wrongs, and not only to Forgive, but alſo to expreſs Kindneſs to the greateſt Criminals; inſomuch that <hi>Iob</hi> had the Confidence, in the heat of his Paſſion, to tell Him, That <hi>He Loved his Enemies more than his Friends,</hi> and, by ſo doing, <hi>Shamed the Faces of all his Servants,</hi> 2 Sam: 19.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:192125:48"/>
            <p>All this notwithſtanding, tho' <hi>David</hi> was a Man according to God's own heart a Character which God himſelf gave him) yet the poor Prince found Troubles on every ſide, Firſt he was preſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed by <hi>Saul.</hi> and anon forced to a Controverſie with <hi>Saul</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouſe One while he was in da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ger from Enemies abroad, and another while from diſaffected Men at home. Now he was Conſpired againſt by <hi>Abſalom,</hi> which afflicted hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the more <hi>Becauſe the Rebel was his Son.</hi> Then he was railed at by <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that Dog (as <hi>Abiſhai</hi> rightly call'd him) the Sier of all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r, which are continually Yelping at the Lords Annoynted. Nor was this all, For <hi>Sheba</hi> and his Fellow Traytors raiſed a formidable In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urrection againſt him, being fruſtrated of their expectations at the Kings Return: For <hi>David</hi> had been in Exile, being <hi>Forced to Fly</hi> [or withdraw] from his Rebellious <hi>Subjects,</hi> and upon his happy Reſtauration <hi>Some Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> were enraged, that They had not that Intereſt at Court which They hoped for; and hereupon They were vexed that the King was come home, and ſo an Alarm was ſounded, <hi>Every Man to his Tents,</hi> O <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, 2 Sam:</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>Had not the Divine Providence been <hi>David</hi>'s Shield and Salvation, that Excellent Prince had been utterly <hi>Ruin'd by This Army of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> which continually follow'd him at the Heels. But God was his ſupport and ſtay; and tho' there was Plot upon Plot, and <hi>Rebellion af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Rebellion, Yet He</hi> truſted ſtill to the <hi>Righteousneſs of His Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> Commemorates with thankfullneſs throughout this his Book of <hi>Pſalms</hi> God's unwearied goodneſs and ſingular Mercy towards him, From whence he draws this Concluſion, for the comfort of all Righteo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Princes, which ſhould come after; that tho' God may, and many times doth, <hi>For great Ends and Reaſons,</hi> ſuffer <hi>Them to be Evil Entreated for a Time;</hi> yet he will not only be with them in their Troubles, but alſo will (ſooner or later) give Them a fair Exit, out of all their diſtreſs Many are the Afflictions of the Righteous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are <hi>Some,</hi> who have gain'd ſuch a perfect Maſtery over their Conſciences, that they can believe even a <hi>Cheat</hi> that ſerveth their turn, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blieve even a Miracle that wounds their Intereſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> diſcerning Men have ſeen for ſeveral years laſt paſt, that our King and Government were both in eminent danger becauſe thoſe very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifices being Imploy'd again, which ſerved effectually to deſtroy the Father, <hi>We</hi> had all the reaſon to believe they were intended to Dethron the Son too; it being impoſſible, but the ſame means uſed in the ſame manner, muſt tend to the accompliſhment of the ſame Ends.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:192125:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:192125:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:192125:50"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Some Men</hi> by their tacit Confeſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and Artificial ſhifts; by exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating and mincing matters [by their d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng publickly to excuſe themſelves (at the Kings requeſt) from the fouleſt charge that was ever drawn againſt Prelates] did force all men to conclude, that there was ſome great thing in hand, which needed the utmoſt of their Art and Skill [which they have ſince moſt lewdly brought to its accu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection] And I am apt to think that Theſe men who can call <hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> only <hi>Innocence,</hi> will ſo leſſen the matter, that Cutting of Throats will be termed only a new way of Triming, and the Deſtruction <hi>[or Dethron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing]</hi> of Princes, to be no more but a <hi>Perfecting the Hiſtory of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who could imagin, that after ſo many Proteſtations and Profeſſions of ſorrow for former miſcarriages! after ſo many vows of Loyalty and hearty Obedience! after ſo many Oaths of All<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>giance and Supremacy, repeated over the whole Nation! after ſuch Acts of Indemnity granted even to Monſters of Rebells! after ſuch prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Royal Bounty, whereby Villains were enriched and grew fat! after ſo many expreſſions of Goodneſs, Tenderneſs and Clemency, enough to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ften any Devils but Fanaticks! after ſo many ſpecious Adreſſes, ſaid to be preſented by his Majeſties <hi>Moſt Dutifull and Loyal Subjects!</hi> I ſay, who could ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that <hi>after all This,</hi> any Such men ſhould be found among <hi>Us,</hi> that would not only Conſpire againſt the King [but have now Helliſhly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged Themſelves in an open Rebellion againſt Him.] But methinks if <hi>Men</hi> would but ſeriously conſider, how the Providence of God hath been particularly concerned for our King all along, from his Birth even to this day [in delivering him from dangers and freeing him from the Miſchievous Imaginations of Wicked Men, <hi>&amp;c.]</hi> it ſhould be enough to turn the hearts of all his Enemies, and prevail with <hi>Them</hi> to love his Government and Him, who hath continually been, <hi>And Still is,</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully preſerved by the immediate Care of Heaven. I have heard of a <hi>Iew</hi> that was Converted to the Chriſtian Faith, by conſidering theſe Wonders of Chriſt for the King.</p>
            <p>Though the generality of Men have been ſtrangely <hi>Blinded</hi> and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead, by the Artifices of <hi>Thoſe,</hi> who made uſe of Mens Fears of Popery, to promote their own Fanatick and Republican Intereſts; Yet there were [and ſtill are] <hi>Many</hi> that will not be wrought upon <hi>To bow down their knees to</hi> Baal; [or <hi>Worſhip the Golden Calf which Same Men have ſet up] We</hi> have all pretended gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at Honour and Affections for his Majeſty, and a moſt tender care for his ſafety and preſervation. But
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:192125:50"/> 
               <hi>We</hi> can never be Loyal or good Subjects, till <hi>We</hi> appl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our ſelves hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily to the neceſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> buſineſs of Repen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance, and <hi>Turn from the Evil of our ways;</hi> We ought to make it the buſineſs of our whole life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Truly</hi> to Fear and Obey God, And then we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eed not fear the moſt Malicious and Wicked Parties of <hi>Thoſe</hi> who have baſely gon off from the King's Side (if ever they were really on it) And gon off too, with all ſorts of <hi>Debauchery</hi> and <hi>Immorality</hi> along with <hi>Them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis neceſſary too that <hi>Men</hi> repent of their <hi>Follies,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Has the <hi>P: O:</hi> kept to his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration?</note> that they have been ſo credulous and eaſy, In <hi>taking the words,</hi> and truſting to the Principles, and ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tting (tho' <hi>Inadvertently)</hi> the Practices of theſe Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators; And to beware of the like Follies for the future. Thoſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples which have been ſent ſo thick abroad of late, That the King hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not his Crown <hi>Jure divino,</hi> but is the Common Wealths Truſtee and Delegate; That he is accountable to his People; That all his Rights are founded upon Human Laws, That He is a Co-Ordinat State; And that the Supreme or Soveraign Power is Lodged in the People: Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did <hi>Theſe Doctrines</hi> tend, but to the Depoſition and Deſtruction [or B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niſhment] of his Majeſty? you may obſerve they were the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples which <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> went upon at the Kings T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yal.</p>
            <p>The manifeſt obſtructing the Courſe of Juſtice, notwithſtanding full and pregnant Evidence; The protecting of the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſeſt F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ows, and the greateſt Cri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>als, who had nothing to recommend them but this, that They were Factious and Dishoneſt; The taking of Oaths, not in the ſenſe of the Law, but according to every Mans priva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e conſtruction; The ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying of the moſt infamous villains; and the zealous endeavours which have been uſed, both to reſcue Traytors from the Law, and to cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anſe their Reputation, af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er they were condemned for the fouleſt Malefactors Whither did all thi's tend, but to embolden Conſpirators, and to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them with ſecurities from all manner of Penalty, if they had but the Character of true Proteſtants? <note n="*" place="margin">A character of the Popiſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lot.</note> The Suborning of Wretches, to ſay and unſay, to ſpeak by Roat, and to tell every thing but truth; The Supporting of Perjury as a Trade, far more profitable than any old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Manufacture; and the Stitching up of every hole, which any Common <hi>Idiot</hi> could ſee in an improbable Story, What did this tend to, but to keep a great ſtock of Oaths in Bank, to ſwear the King himſelf out of his Honour and his Life? The Charge and Sweat which Thouſands have waſted, to put the moſt Diſaffected perſons into
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:192125:51"/> Places and Offices of great Truſt, and Power! What did this tend to, but to make Reſiſtance and Rebellion look fair with the Face of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity? the aſperſing of the Government; the Calumniating of his Majeſty, and all Subordinate Magiſtrates, and Loyal Miniſters of State; The Frightning of Men with ſuch a noiſe of Popery, when ſo many had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed all Religion for Atheiſm; The Out-cry againſt Tyrany, when the Licenciousneſs of thoſe very men argued that Common Juſtice could not be done, no, not for the King himſelf; What did all this tend to but to Subvert the Fundamental Conſtitution both in Church and State? The diſperſing of Libells; The Countenancing of the moſt Seditious <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets,</hi> that came from the Rudeſt and Fllthieſt hands; The Scareing of Men (if it had been poſſible) from ſpeaking Reaſon, Juſtice or Truth; And the practicing of every thing that ſerv'd for the diminution of all that is Good, Great, and Noble; What did all this tend to, but to help Evil-minded Men by degrees and Inches to get to the king's Throne, that they might Aſſaffinate his Perſon with a full Thruſt, and then leave it to the prejudiced and ill affected world to make their Appology.</p>
            <p>One would have thought it impoſſible, that diſcerning Men ſhould not be able to look to the end of theſe things, nor ſo much as to gueſs at the Concluſion by the premiſſes: But ſo it was that great multitudes of Men (Some of whom I am peſwaded were not guilty of Black Intentions) were led away with the Common Error, and upon <hi>falſe preſumptions; That nothing was at the Bottom, but a tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Deſign for the Intereſt and Stability of Religion;</hi> The Stale pretence that turn'd the Nation into <hi>Aceldema</hi> once before! 'Tis High time therefore for ſuch to be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſee how greatly They were befool'd, and to conſider with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves how far they may have contributed (tho' unwittingly) to the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on a Deſign <hi>Soe Horrid and Barbarous</hi> without a Parallel; and by their juſt Indignation for what is paſt, and Higheſt zeal for the future, to endeavour (if it be poſſible) to make his Majeſty Reparation for thoſe intollerable miſchiefs, which Blood-thirſty Traytors would (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) never have attempted upon the Confidence of their own Intereſt.</p>
            <p>I have no more to add' but that <hi>We</hi> give all dilligence Religiouſly and Honeſtly to perform <hi>Our Duty</hi> to God, and to his Annoynted; and in ſo doing to look up to the Hills from whence all our help cometh, and to trust in God for Our deliverance from <hi>Theſe Dangers</hi> which Stand now dreadfully before <hi>Us,</hi> trusting in Him, who hath heretofore deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered <hi>Us,</hi> that He will deliver <hi>Us</hi> yet Still; Tho the troubles of the Righteous be many, Yet the Lord delivereth him out of all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Abington</hi> next the <hi>Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>der</hi> in <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e-ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:192125:51"/>
            <head>Samaritaniſme Revived, A Sermon Preach'd at Great <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> by <hi>Luke Milbourne</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezra,</hi> 4. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THo' wicked men of all kinds are at never ſo great a diſtance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, yet Truth being equally an Enemy to them all, it moves their hatred ſo much againſt it ſelf, that other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſts and Broyls are ſoon forgotten. So the <hi>Phariſees, Sadduces,</hi> and <hi>Herodians</hi> laboured at all times to undermine each other, but readily combined together to deſtroy our Saviour. The more vigorous and bright Truths luſter is, the more violent the aſſaults of its oppoſers, be: So it proved in the Primitive Church, many and abſurd Hereſies ſprung up in it, The breaches between the different Hereticks were irreparable, And yet <hi>They Lived</hi> almoſt in a conſtant <hi>Conſpiracy againſt the True Catholick Church of Chriſt:</hi> And he that examins Church Hiſtory will finde, that when peace gave the greateſt Ornaments to Chriſtianity the <hi>Muſhroon</hi> Hereſies and Schiſms grew up the faſteſt; as on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, when Religion grew indifferent and the Profeſſors of it Lukewarm, Hereticks and Schiſmaticks ſeemed to lay down their Weapons, as if Hell had no more employment for them.</p>
            <p>The Devil is never ſo truly dreadful, as when he puts on the ſhape of an Angel of Light, otherwiſe every one ſtands upon his guard, but then the Subtle Serpent inſinuats himſelf into the boſſoms of thoſe, who leaſt ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect his poyſonous nature. And <hi>Wicked Men</hi> can never poſſibly do ſuch miſchief, as when <hi>They</hi> put on the viſor of Piety; The ſervants of God avoid Them, when they appear like <hi>Themſelves,</hi> But when the ſheeps Clothing has inveſted the Wolf, even he may paſs for a very Innocent Creature.</p>
            <p>It is not to be queſtion'd, but that the acknowledgment of the True God, and the offering due ſacrifices to him as God, is the main Foundation of True Religion: But a bare Foundation without a Superſtructure is of on worth, for upon theſe Principles plainly and evidently depend a great number of other things, which, if not obſerved, prove that the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:192125:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:192125:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:192125:53"/> was never truly own'd; For if a man believe indeed that there is a God, and by offering Sacrifices, acknowledgeth there is a duty ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that God, nothing can be commanded by that God, nothing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, but the man (if he hopes for Salvation) muſt ſincerely, and to the utmoſt of his power obey it. <hi>All the Commands</hi> of God muſt be punctually obey'd; <hi>Men</hi> may not cull out this, or another, according to their own Fancies, ſince the Rule is infallibly Authentick, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2, 10. That whoſoever ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet offend in one point, he is guilty of all; The reaſon is becauſe he breaks that very Foundation he builds upon <hi>viz.)</hi> The confeſſion of a God, and our duty to Him: The Apoſtle makes the inference, <hi>verſe</hi> the 11: For He that ſaid do not commit <hi>Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ery,</hi> ſaid alſo, do not <hi>Kill;</hi> now if thou commit no <hi>Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> yet if thou <hi>Kill</hi> Thou art become a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ranſgreſſor of the Law: ſo then if any man pretend, out of a ſenſe of his duty to God, to do one or more things, and yet mindes not ſome other things, which God has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded aſwell as thoſe, <hi>His whole Obedience is nothing,</hi> and his whole pretence a Lye, he really (with the Fool) ſays in his heart, there is no God.</p>
            <p>But if at laſt we look into the word of God, we ſhall find that as he has commanded us to abſtain from all Immoralities, even from whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever has the leaſt appearance of Evil; ſo he has by the Apoſtle enjoyn'd <hi>Us</hi> to mark, to ſet a brand of infamy on Thoſe, which cauſe Diviſions and Offences, contrary to the Doctrine We have learned, and to avoid them, 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 5, 22. For <hi>They</hi> that are ſuch ſerve not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt but their own Belly, and by good words and fair ſpeeches <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Hearts of the People, Rom:</hi> 16 17, 18. It is not the openeſs of a Sin that makes it comparitively the greater; Malice is as bad as Theft, yet it lys cloſe conceal'd within the dark Receſſes of the heart; Witchcraft is an obſcure Sin, few know what it is, yet every one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves it worſe than <hi>Drunkeneſs, Adultery, Covetuousneſs,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> tho' it hates the light, is as had as <hi>Profaneſs.</hi> To Curſe the King in <hi>Our</hi> hearts (tho' never ſo ſecretly) is a Damnable Sin, And 'tis the ſame <hi>To contrive Tumults and Rebellions in the State, againſt Our Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Soveraign.</hi> But theſe laſt admit of one particular aggrava<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all bare Immoralities whatſoever; and it is this, every one who pretends to Conſcience acknowledges it to be his duty, to abjure all Immoralities, while many pretend to be active in the other only for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, And when Sin is once abetted by that which men call Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the miſchievous effects of it know no bounds.</p>
            <p>Preſently after the King's Reſtauration, before things wre fully ſettled
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:192125:53"/> 
               <hi>Tong, Phillips, Stubbs, Hind, Sallers, Gibbs,</hi> (all of 'Em men pretending to tender Conſciences) were executed at <hi>Tyburn 22 Decemb.</hi> 1662. for no meaner a deſign than Cutting off Root and Branch, <hi>Kings! Queens! Dukes! Biſhop!</hi> all were to go one way! <hi>That there ſhould be no Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beyond Seas,</hi> or parlyes there, but a Total deſtruction of the <hi>King, Lords, Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Gentry;</hi> The Plot when effected to be <hi>Charged upon the Papiſts,</hi> and the People to be excited to Riſe in Arms under pretence of a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Maſſacre; And the Godly party in the year following were <hi>Plotting</hi> again (in the <hi>Northern</hi> parts) to carry on the ſame work their Brethren had failed in before; Of which Treaſonable Plot; His Majeſty told the two Houſes, That it was of a large extent, and very near execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, had not he by God's goodneſs come to the knowledg of the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal contrivers, and ſo ſecured them from doing their intended miſchief. But ſtill the Evil Spirit was not quite lay'd, In the year 1666 the ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Parties ventur'd once more upon a Plot, To Murder His Majeſty, Overthrow the Government, Surpriſe the <hi>Tower,</hi> Kill the <hi>Lord</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and to <hi>Fire the City of London,</hi> which Plot was to have been exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted <hi>September</hi> the third of that year: Mony was diſtributed to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators, and a Council of the Heads ſetled at <hi>London</hi> for the Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of affairs: For which <hi>Helliſh Plot Rathbone, Saunders, Tuck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, Flint, Evans, Myles, Weſtcot,</hi> and <hi>Cole,</hi> were executed. And tho' ſo many ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, yet one part of the <hi>Plot</hi> was unhappily effected in that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Conflagration wherein the great Metropolis of the Kingdom was lay'd in <hi>Aſhes.</hi> This being diſappointed the Devil of Sedition flew into <hi>Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tland,</hi> when in the ſame year the Old Covenanters broke out into Rebellion, at <hi>Pentland</hi> hills, ſoon after <hi>Iames, Mitchel</hi> (a Covenanting Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter) attempted the Aſſaſſination of Dr. <hi>Sharp,</hi> the moſt Reverend Arch-Biſhop of St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> and in the attempt mortally wounded the Biſhop of <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y:</hi> But the poor Arch-biſhop eſcaped not ſo; Implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Fanatiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n purſued, 'till he was effectually Murdered by ſome of the Crew (with the moſt inexpreſſible barbarity) <hi>3d May</hi> 1679, The ſame month a new Rebellion (under the Banner of the Covenant) broke out at <hi>Bothwell Bridge,</hi> where Their Powers were cruſh'd once again; From which blow God grant <hi>They</hi> never more return. But all theſe ill Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, have not yet <hi>(It ſeems)</hi> ſo tamed our numerous Sectaries, <hi>and their Favourers,</hi> but that <hi>Religious Treaſon</hi> has once more made its Entry among <hi>Us;</hi> The King himſelf, the Duke, the great Officers of State, the Loyal Magiſtrates of the City of <hi>London,</hi> all doom'd to Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>!</hi> No <hi>Slave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y!</hi> has been the Common Cry, <hi>They</hi> act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein like thoſe Sabtle villains, who when they have Killed a man
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:192125:54"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:192125:54"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:192125:55"/> themſelves, are the moſt buſie to find out the Murderers. <hi>Same tell us,</hi> that he Members of the laſt Parliament at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> were <hi>All Church Men;</hi> But what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey were, their horrid actions declared, <hi>Such Church Men</hi> the true Church of <hi>England</hi> will always diſown, as only fit Aſſociats for Conſpirators and Rebells.</p>
            <p>Is † <hi>This the True Proteſtancy ſome have boaſted ſo much of? Or are all P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piſhly aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted who declar can Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Rebellion now on Foc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>abhorrence of all ſuch D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iliſh Principles and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces?</hi> May <hi>We</hi> all bear that reproac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ful Character, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than for a Popular Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, run headlong to the Devil. And let all Perſons, who profeſs Loyalty to their Soveraign be truly Loyal to that God, who is the great preſerver of Princes; Let the world be convinced, that even ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eming virtues, which render Schiſmaticks plauſible, are ſolid <hi>and</hi> real in all Thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, who maintain God's ancient, ſolemn &amp; r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lar wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; Let <hi>Us</hi> Fear God and Honour and Truſt our Soveraign; Let no Subtle Emiſſarles of Faction, make <hi>Us</hi> ſuſpicious of our Superiours, or of one another, That ſo We preſerving the unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace and Righteousneſs of Life, the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k of God may proſper in Our hands; That <hi>Plots Treaſons</hi> and <hi>Rebellions</hi> againſt Our Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Prince, may for ever be execra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed and accurſed, And all <hi>England</hi> may hear and fear, And no ſuch <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ckedneſs</hi> may be hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of among <hi>Us</hi> any more. <hi>London</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <head>A Sermon Preach'd at <hi>Weſtminſter Abby</hi> on the <hi>29th</hi> of <hi>July</hi> 1685, being the Thanksgiving day for Quelling <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Rebellion, by <hi>Edward Pelling,</hi> Chaplain to the Duke of <hi>Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſett.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal:</hi> 124. 6.</bibl>
               <q>Bleſſed be the Lord, who hath not given us as a Prey to <hi>Their</hi> Teeth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe good Providence of God over the Sacred Perſons and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Princes in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſerving both from the moſt Malicious deſigns of ſo many Reſtleſs and Sanguinary Spirits, is one of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:192125:55"/> the moſt ſtupendious works of God's Omnipotence, that ever He hath ſhew'd ſince the laſt day of the Creation, a Miracle which was the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Subject of King <hi>David</hi>'s thankfull M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>itations (up and down throughout his whole Book of <hi>Pſalms)</hi> and pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>icularly in this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> where after a moſt humble manner he doth adore the infinite Mercy and Power of God, For <hi>Delivering Him and his Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts,</hi> from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>reat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dangers of a freſh Inſurrection: And that too, when the Rebellion was ſo formidable, When the Malice of <hi>Wicked Men</hi> was ſo outragious; when their app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tites were not to be ſatisfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d but with ſtreams of Blood, when Ruin was breaking in upon the whole land like a mighty Torrent, when without the immediate help of God, nothing could be expected but utter deſolation; when the danger was ſo emminent, and ſeemingly ſo inevitable, that <hi>Thoſe Men</hi> of <hi>Uiolence</hi> thought themſelves as ſure, as if the Prey they ſought after, were already in the Gin; Then was the time for God to lay to his hand, to make bare his Arm, and to gain himſelf Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our <note n="*" place="margin">ſo was the King Delivered from Rocheſter.</note> by reſeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng <hi>Innocence</hi> from the Pitt, as it lay at the Brink, ready to drop into the depth of Deſtruction. And this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ger did proceed from <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eba</hi> and his Aſſociates; a deſperate Leader of a <hi>Uery Terrible Defection;</hi> nothing being more dangerous to any Prince, than the <hi>United</hi> Malice of Rebellions Spirits, that ſubmit, not for Conſcience ſake, but either upon Conſtraint, or for <hi>Their</hi> Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt only.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but <hi>David</hi> in the Penning of this <hi>Pſalm</hi> particularly thought of the Conſpyracy of his Bloody Son <hi>Abſolom,</hi> that formerly had been guilty of ſhameful Murder; his <hi>Ambitious</hi> Son <hi>Abſolom, whom nothing would ſatisfy but the Crown;</hi> his ungratful Son <hi>Abſolom,</hi> that ſo baſely rewarded him for his Longings after him, when he fled from his preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce to <hi>Geſhur,</hi> and for his pardon, for his Kiſſes upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn; His <hi>Perſidious</hi> Son <hi>Abſolom,</hi> that no ſooner went out of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Court, but ran to the Gates, to ſteal away the hearts of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Subjects, ſaying <hi>O that I were made Iudge</hi> (meaning King) in the Land; His <hi>Hypocritycal</hi> Son <hi>Abſolom</hi> that pretending a deſire to perform his vow <hi>[To preſerve the Proteſtant Religion</hi> &amp;c.] would have Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the <hi>Throne</hi> and did under colour of Religion raiſe an open and bare-fac'd R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bellion. <hi>This</hi> was ſuch a dreadful Conſpiracy, as made <hi>David</hi> himſelf [the King] tho' a man of ſuch Proweſs and Conduct, preſently <hi>To fly for his Life.</hi> Such a <hi>Uiolent agitation</hi> were People in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that they were ready to flow to him from all Quarters, like the meeting and inundation of many Rivers to make a Deluge.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:192125:56"/>
            <p>And that which made this Conſpiracy the more Terrible was that <hi>Achitophel</hi> was in the head of many others. <hi>Achitophel</hi> that hardned Traytor, and curſed Reprobate, that when his Council and Bloody en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours would not take, fled for it preſently, and through Anguiſh and Vexation Hang'd himſelf: A ſad end indeed, for any Rebel to be his own Executioner, though in <hi>Some</hi> Caſes 'tis pitty that an <hi>Achitophel,</hi> an <hi>Inveterate and Adviſing Rebel</hi> ſhould ever dye in his Bed.</p>
            <p>When the Higheſt <hi>Treaſon</hi> was form'd by ſuch working Heads, when 'twas Conducted by ſuch Politick Councils; when 'twas Executed by ſuch deſperate Inſtruments; when it proſper'd <hi>On a ſuddain by ſuch</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">The vileſt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherys of ſome of the Nobility, in the Weſt.</note> 
               <hi>Succeſſful Stratagems,</hi> nothing could be expected, but the <hi>King's</hi> inevitable Ruin, had not the hand of God been more concern'd in the cauſe, than the hand of <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>Faithful</hi> General, <hi>Joab;</hi> viſible in the ſurprizing death of <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom,</hi> Who was caught in a wood, and hung by his Locks upon a Tree; To ſhew the World what a Reward all <hi>They</hi> deſerve that take up <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> and Rebel againſt <hi>Their</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Is not James the 2d Son of Charles the firſt and only brother of Charles the 2d who dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without Iſſue.</note> 
               <hi>Lawful Prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis true <hi>(a moſt ſad and ſhameful Truth God knows)</hi> ſuch was the monſtrous Impiety of the laſt Age, that it afforded one unpreſidented, unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd inſtance of God's wrath, when that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Monarch, the Glory of our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and Honour of the world, was forced to bow his head down, and to fall a Sacrifice, to the Luſts of the moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Villains, <note n="†" place="margin">Somthing like the caſe of his preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties; But God be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it is not go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo far!</note> as if God had forſaken him! however that ſome Compenſation might be made for that ſuperlative (and otherwiſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) loſs, by the due Succeſſion, and after greatneſs of his Poſterity, God hath multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed thoſe Temporal Glories upon the Sons, which he took from the Father, and gave him a bleſſed Eternity in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for. And to let the world ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> is criminal even when tis proſperous, and to puniſh Rebellion, in a Second Age, <hi>tho' it eſcaped in the Firſt,</hi> God hath delivered the <hi>Two Royal Brothers,</hi> from ſix Troub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aven, too' <hi>Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ba</hi> and <hi>Abſolom,</hi> with their Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Confederats <hi>[or Inviters]</hi> joyn'd hand to hand to execute a Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, which had been long a forming by the <note n="*" place="margin">For the People are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wais deceived by the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Pretence, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp;c. as the Serpent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Eve, with the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the fruit. And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent as she did when 'tis too late.</note> Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pentine Subtilty of a twining and party-colour'd <hi>Achitophel.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:192125:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>This Deliverance was manifeſtly the work of God. Our dangers were ſo immenſe, and and yet ſo cloſe and privy, that it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h paſſed the Sagacity, and exceeded the reach of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Force to prevent them, and nothing can deliver Us from them but the Power and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Almighty God, What were the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators, but the moſt daring and deſperate Villains? And what was the Conſpiracy itſelf, but along ſtudied, and now ripe Deſign, to draw in <hi>upon Us an whole Deluge of Blood</hi> to over-whelm Prince and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with final Slaughter, <hi>To deſtroy the very name,</hi> aſwell as to ſtiflle all further efforts of <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and to bury <hi>Ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Monarch</hi> [or <hi>Dethrone</hi> him] beyond all hopes of a Reſurrection? and what is like to be at the end of all this, but Irreligion and <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eiſm,</hi> accompanied with the moſt diſmal Confuſions, and a <hi>Perpetual War,</hi> till by weak'ning and killing one another, We may in time, when 'tis to late grow weary of <hi>Our</hi> Follies.</p>
            <p>Good God! That ever <hi>Atheiſm</hi> ſhould prevail in ſuch a Land as this, where not only all Demonſtrative Arguments have been uſed to prove a being infinitely wiſe, Juſt, and Good, to preſide over the world, but moreover where the preſence of God hath been ſo often, ſo long, and in all the viciſſitudes and changes of this Sublunary World, ſo conſtantly ſeen and manifeſted, as if he had taken up his abode with <hi>Us,</hi> as if he had ſaid of tkis Kingdom, as he did of <hi>Zion, Pſal.</hi> 132. 14. This is my Reſt for ever; Here will I dwell, for I have a delight therein; And yet I may truly ſay, but to our great ſhame, <hi>that ſince the Creation of the Univerſe there never was ſuch an Atheſtical Generation,</hi> no, not in the moſt dark; in the moſt diſtant; in the moſt infidel parts of the World, as this Nation hath groaned under theſe late years.</p>
            <p>And yet 'tis obſervable (tho' it be very ſtrange) that <hi>None</hi> among <hi>Us</hi> have pretended greater concernment for the Reformation, than Thoſe who have bid open defiance to all Religion whatſoever <hi>Men</hi> of the moſt profligate Reputation: Open <hi>Drunkards,</hi> profeſt <hi>Adul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> Notorious Cheats, <hi>Forſworn Rebells,</hi> Impudent Lyars, <hi>Perſidious Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites,</hi> and but the other day Scoff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs at God, and at the very ſhew of Piety. <hi>'Tis enough to move the Meekeſt, the moſt Patient Man on Earth to conſider what Foreheads of Steel and Adamant thoſe Impious Wretches, haue that coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> take the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nſidence Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to Gull and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon the People, by a ſeeming Zeal for Religion: Eſpecially when They are now up in Arms, fighting for it; in open Rebellion againſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:192125:57"/> the Example of our Saviour, and the Precepts of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As far as I have obſerved, the whole Hiſtory of <hi>England</hi> doth not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Us an Inſtance of God's Providence, that can come any thing near that account which Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tes to our preſent Soveraign, and his Royal Brother Deceaſed; unleſs it be that ſingle Story of King <hi>Alfred</hi> the great: A Prince of that Learning Wiſdom, Clemency, Sweetneſs of nature, and other ſuch excellent Virtues, as really made him an honour and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament to the Throne. And yet that excellent Prince was once Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to thoſe miſerable ſtraights partly by the Invaſion of Enemies from abroad, and partly through the Treachery of Rebels and Deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at Home, that he was Forc'd to put himſelf into the diſguiſe once of a Common Soldier, another time of an Herds-man, and at laſt to abſcond for a conſiderable time in the Weſt, in a poor Cottage, among Woods and Moors (a ſad and wofull place for a Crown'd Head to Reſt in!) And yet ſuch was his Religious dependance upon God, that tho' He was <hi>Forſaken by his Friends,</hi> invioron'd with his Enemies, and brought to thoſe extreams and ſhameful neceſſities, that his mother and himſelf were hardly able to ſubſiſt, yet <hi>He doubted not but Providence w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld one Day Reſtore Him to his juſt Grandieur.</hi> And ſo it was, that in that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mean Condition, in that moſt obſcure place he began the Recovery of his Fortunes: There he began the Foundation of his Kingdom, Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it on ſtill by degrees, till in a little time he became the ſole and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Monarch of this Nation, and made it a moſt Flouriſhing Kingdom, and gave many the moſt excellent Laws that We enjoy at this Hour, or rather may ſo do, when God ſhall Reſtore the King, and we return to to Our Allegiance and Duties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Keble</hi> at the <hi>Turks Head</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Error</hi> Pag: 2, line laſt Read their Shoulders.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:192125:57"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>NOw Reader! (after Thou haſt duly conſider'd theſe <hi>Firm</hi> Doctrines, of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion) Tell me truly, If thou canſt expect ever to ſee One Rebel in Heaven, or to meet even any of Thoſe, that do but wiſh proſperity to Rebellion, in the Regions of Bliſs? Tell me, if thou haſt any dread of a Future Judgment! If thou haſt any value for thy Soul! what Rewards will follow Thee! what ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance rather will purſue Thee! if thou ſet up a God of thy own Fancy, and hearken to the Oracles of Rebellion, inſtead of Governing all thy Thoughts words and Actions, by the precepts of the Goſpel, and after the meek example of the Bleſſed Jeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s? Doſt thou think one Murther e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to Damn an unrepenting Soul, and Canſt thou wiſh Succeſs to thoſe that take Arms againſt the King, without Plunging thy ſelf into the Guilt of every Man's Blood that is, or ſhall be Spilt, in ſuch a Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Quarrel? Canſt thou Offer in Sacrifice, thy will and affections (as the <hi>Indians</hi> do their darling Children to the Devil) to the Monſtrous <hi>Idol</hi> of Rebellion, and not be tainted with that <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which will ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitably Damn thy Soul, without a moſt ſpeedy, and the deepeſt Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? Nay tell me if thou canſt Repent, If the Nature of thy Crime, will admit of Repentance in thee, when <hi>Lucifer</hi> was Damn'd, becauſe the Sin of his Rebellion was utterly incapable of that Grace, which gives a true Repentance.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Fare-well.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:192125:58"/>
            <p>Theſe Sermons may be Printed, Dublin Caſtle the 28th of July 1689. Patrick Clogher.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <list>
               <head>Thanksgiving <hi>Sermons</hi> Preached on the <hi>9th</hi> of <hi>September.</hi> 1683.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Francis</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> pag. 37</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Fitz-william,</hi> D. D. pag. 01</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Sherlock,</hi> D. D. pag. 15</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paul Lathom,</hi> Prebend of <hi>Sarum,</hi> pag. 20</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Benjamin Calamy,</hi> D. D. pag. 25</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Bolton</hi> Scholmaſter of the <hi>Charter-houſe.</hi> pag. 30</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Price,</hi> D. D. pag. 33</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Charles Powel,</hi> M. A. pag. 43</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Smith</hi> Prebend of <hi>Norwich,</hi> pag. 47</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Miles Barnes,</hi> D. D. pag. 51</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Hesketh,</hi> Miniſter of St. <hi>Hellens</hi> pag. 55</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Harriſon,</hi> D. D. pag. 58</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Edward Pelling,</hi> D. D. pag. 60</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Luke Milbourne</hi> pag. 65</item>
               <item>A Thanksgiving <hi>Sermon</hi> againſt <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 29th July.</hi> 1685.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Edward Pelling,</hi> D. D. pag. 68</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
